<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A fountain sealed: or, The duty of the sealed to the Spirit, and the worke of the Spirit in sealing. Wherein many things are handled about the Holy Spirit, and grieving of it: as also of assurance and sealing what it is, the priviledges and degrees of it, with the signes to discerne, and means to preserve it. : Being the substance of divers sermons preached at Grayes Inne. / By that Reverend Divine, Richard Sibbes D.D. and sometimes preacher to that honourable society.</title>
            <author>Sibbes, Richard, 1577-1635.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 196 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 139 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00698</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22496</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S123290</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">44920430</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 44920430</idno>
            <idno type="VID">173875</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00698)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 173875)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2104:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A fountain sealed: or, The duty of the sealed to the Spirit, and the worke of the Spirit in sealing. Wherein many things are handled about the Holy Spirit, and grieving of it: as also of assurance and sealing what it is, the priviledges and degrees of it, with the signes to discerne, and means to preserve it. : Being the substance of divers sermons preached at Grayes Inne. / By that Reverend Divine, Richard Sibbes D.D. and sometimes preacher to that honourable society.</title>
                  <author>Sibbes, Richard, 1577-1635.</author>
                  <author>Goodwin, Thomas, 1600-1680.</author>
                  <author>Nye, Philip, 1596?-1672.</author>
                  <author>Marshall, William, fl. 1617-1650.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 250 p., [1] leaf of plates : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Harper for Lawrence Chapman, and are to be sold at his shop at Chancery lane end, in Holborne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1638.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Epistle dedicatory (p. [8]-[11] at front) signed: Tho. Goodwin. Philip Nye.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-L¹²M⁶ (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Last line of leaf A3 recto begins "Ladyship".</note>
                  <note>Portrait of Richard Sibbes on added engraved t.p., signed, Will: Marshall sculpsit.</note>
                  <note>Head-pieces; initials.</note>
                  <note>Title within double-rule border; text within ruled border.</note>
                  <note>Contains marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, tightly bound, and with print show-through; slight loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Ephesians IV, 30 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Holy Spirit --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="engraved_title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:173875:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>A FOUNTAINE SEALED OR <hi>The</hi> Dutie <hi>of the ſealed to the</hi> SPIRIT</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the</hi> worke <hi>of the Spirit in Sealing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By <hi>Rich: Sibbes, D. D. The 3<hi rend="sup">d.</hi> Edition.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Printed for L: Chapman &amp; are to be ſould at his ſhope at Chancery Lane end in Holborne.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>will: Marſhall. ſculpsit.</hi> 1638.</p>
                  <figDesc>engraved title page</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:173875:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173875:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A FOUNTAIN SEALED: <hi>OR,</hi> The <hi>duty</hi> of the ſealed to the Spirit, and the <hi>worke</hi> of the Spirit in Sealing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein</hi> Many things are handled about the Holy Spirit, and grieving of it:</p>
            <p>As alſo Of aſſurance and ſealing what it is, the priviledges and degrees of it, with the ſignes to diſcerne, and meanes to preſerve it. Being The ſubſtance of divers Sermons prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at <hi>Grayes Inne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By that Reverend Divine, RICHARD SIBBES, D. D. and ſometimes Preacher to that Honourable Society.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Thomas Harper,</hi> for <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence Chapman,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at Chancery lane end, in Holborne, 1638.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:173875:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173875:3"/>
            <head>To The truly Noble, and much honoured Lady, the Lady <hi>Elizabeth Brooke,</hi> Wife to Sir <hi>Robert Brooke.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madame:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eſides that deſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ved in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt your Ladyſhip held in the
<pb facs="tcp:173875:4"/>fections and eſteeme of this worthy man more then any friend alive, which might intitle you to all that may call him Authour. This ſmall piece of his acknowledgeth a more ſpeciall propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety unto your Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. For though his tongue was as the Pen of a ready Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the hand of Chriſt who guided
<pb facs="tcp:173875:4"/>him, yet your Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips hand and Pen was in this his ſcribe and Amanuenſis whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt hee dictated a firſt draught of it in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, with intention for the publique. Jn which labour both of humility and love, your <hi>Ladyſhip</hi> did that honour unto him which <hi>Baruch</hi> (thogh great and Noble) did but receive in the
<pb facs="tcp:173875:5"/>like, tranſcribing the words of <hi>Ieremiah,</hi> from his mouth: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in yet your <hi>Ladyſhip</hi> did indeed, but write the ſtory of your owne life, which hath beene long exactly framed to the rules herein preſcribed. We there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that are intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in the publiſhing of it, deeme it but an act of Juſtice in us to return it thus to your
<pb facs="tcp:173875:5"/>Ladyſhip, unto whom it owes, even its firſt Birth: that ſo where ever <hi>this</hi> little Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe <hi>ſhall come, there alſo this that you have done, may bee told and recorded for a memorial of you.</hi> And wee could not but eſteeme it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo an addition of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to the worke, that no leſſe then a Ladies hand (ſo pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="tcp:173875:6"/>&amp; ſo much honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) brought it forth into the world, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in it ſelfe it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth as much as any other this bleſſed wombe did beare. The Lord in way of recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, write all the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Contents of it, yet more fully and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly in your Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips heart, and all the lineaments of the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:173875:6"/>and <hi>ſeale</hi> up all unto you <hi>by his</hi> bleſſed <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> with joy and peace <hi>to the day of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madame,</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>we are your Ladyſhips devoted,</hi> THO. GOODWIN. PHILIP NYE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:173875:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173875:7"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Rieve not the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit of God.</hi> The Holy Ghoſt why called a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, <hi>page 3</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Why holy, <hi>page 5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>From the Apoſtles diſſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, theſe foure preſuppoſed truths.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1</hi> That the holy Ghoſt is in us, <hi>page 8</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2</hi> And is as a guide to us, <hi>page 12</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3</hi> The beſt of us are apt to grieve him, <hi>page 13</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:173875:8"/>
                        <hi>4</hi> Therefore wee ſhould bee carefull of it, <hi>page 14</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>§ <hi>1. Of grieving the Spirit.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>I</hi> What it is to grieve the Spirit, <hi>16.</hi> how the Spirit wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in us, <hi>page 20</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>II</hi> Wherein doe we eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grieve the Spirit.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1</hi> In our ſelves, and that in theſe particulars.
<list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>1</hi> In walking contrary to, and in neglecting of its moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>25.</hi> and comforts, <hi>27.</hi> ſeeking comfort from the fleſh, <hi>page 28</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>2</hi> By unkindeneſſe, <hi>29.</hi> the ſinnes of Profeſſors, and thoſe that have moſt acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with the Spirit, grieve moſt, <hi>page 30</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>3</hi> By preſumptuous ſinnes, <hi>33,</hi> ſinnes againſt knowledge
<pb facs="tcp:173875:8"/>of two ſorts. <hi>ibid.</hi> why volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary ſinnes are ſo great, and grieve the Spirit ſo much, <hi>36,</hi> the reaſon why ſinnes of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Table grieve moſt, <hi>39,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on divers reſpects the ſame ſort of ſinnes may grieve more and leſſe, <hi>page 44</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>4</hi> By worldlineſſe and pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tribute to the fleſh, <hi>page 45</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>5</hi> Abuſing ſpirituall things to our owne ends, <hi>48.</hi> and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering the workes of the fleſh upon the ſpirit, <hi>page 49</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>6</hi> By ſins againſt the Goſpell, <hi>49,</hi> ſlighting ordinances, <hi>page 51</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>7</hi> Sinnes plotted and contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, <hi>page 57</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>8</hi> By falſe judgement of things, <hi>page 55</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>9</hi> By not uſing the helpes we have, <hi>page 58</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>10</hi> Cavelling againſt the truth, <hi>page 59</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <pb facs="tcp:173875:9"/>
                                    <hi>11</hi> By doing duty in our owne ſtrength, <hi>page 61</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>12</hi> Thruſting our ſelves into over-much worldly employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>61,</hi> whence,</item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>13</hi> Omiſsion or ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>ght perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of duty, <hi>page 63</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2</hi> In others many ways, as
<list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Neglecting the grace in them, <hi>page 65</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>2</hi> Sharpe cenſures, <hi>page 65</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>3</hi> Superiours by unjuſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, <hi>page 66</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>4</hi> Inferiours by untractable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>5</hi> By evill examples, <hi>page 68</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>III</hi> How we may know when we have grieved the ſpirit, <hi>69</hi> and what is the danger of it, <hi>page 71</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>How farre a childe of God may grieve the Spirit. <hi>page 76</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Of the ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>81,</hi> and a twofold miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage
<pb facs="tcp:173875:9"/>about it in cenſuring, <hi>page 82</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>IIII</hi> What courſe we ſhould take to prevent grieving the Spirit <hi>84,</hi> in divers rules.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1</hi> Give your ſelfe up to the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of it, <hi>page 84</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2</hi> Subject conſtantly to the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits motions: they are knowne from other motions.
<list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>1</hi> By a ſpeciall ſtrength in them, by which they are raiſed to higher ends, <hi>page 87</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>2</hi> By their conſtancy, <hi>page 88</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>3</hi> They proceed from a chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged heart, <hi>page 89</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>4</hi> They are ſeaſonable, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>5</hi> A ſelf evide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in them, <hi>page 90</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>6</hi> Orderly, in reſpect of both Tables of the law, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>7</hi> Dependant upon God, <hi>page 91</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>3</hi> Ioyne and co-operate with the Spirit, <hi>page 92</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>4</hi> Turne motions into reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb facs="tcp:173875:10"/>
                              <hi>94</hi> and reſolutions into practiſe, <hi>page 95</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>5</hi> Depend on ordinances, and get a heart ſuteable to them, <hi>page 96</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>6</hi> Obſerve the Spirits firſt withdrawing, and ſearch the cauſe, <hi>page 100</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>7</hi> Take heed of ſuch ſinnes as wee terme little ones, <hi>102,</hi> and looke upon all ſinne in the riſe and root of it, <hi>104</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>8</hi> Get ſpirituall wiſedome to know what is pleaſing and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing to the Spirit, <hi>page 105</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>9</hi> Vpon breaches, renew repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, <hi>page 108</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>10</hi> Avoyd corrupt communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, <hi>page 109</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Whereby you are ſealed.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>§ <hi>2 Of the ſealing of the Spirit.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1</hi> Chriſt is ſealed, <hi>page 122</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2</hi> So are Chriſtians, <hi>page 125</hi>
                        <list>
                           <pb facs="tcp:173875:10"/>
                           <item>
                              <hi>I</hi> What this ſealing is, and how it is wrought, <hi>page 125</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>II</hi> The priviledges of it.
<list>
                                 <head>A ſeale ſerveth for</head>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Confirmation, <hi>page 131</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>2</hi> Diſtinction, <hi>page 132</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>3</hi> Appropriation, <hi>page 139</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>4</hi> Eſtimation, <hi>page 141</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>5</hi> Secrecy, <hi>page 144</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>6</hi> Security, <hi>page 146</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>III</hi> Degrees of ſealing.
<list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>1</hi> The worke of faith, <hi>page 149</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>2</hi> Sanctification, <hi>150.</hi> yet not without a new act of the Spirit, <hi>153,</hi> the reaſons, <hi>page 155</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>3</hi> Ioy, <hi>156.</hi> which hath its degrees alſo, <hi>158,</hi> being from the ſpirit, <hi>page 159</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Of the three witneſſes on earth, <hi>160,</hi> their order, <hi>page 164,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Of the witneſſe of the Spirit immediately from it ſelfe, which is the higheſt, and that which bringeth moſt joy, <hi>page 166</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <pb facs="tcp:173875:11"/>Of ſuch joyes and raptures of the Spirit, and how they are knowne from illuſions, <hi>Page 169.</hi> as
<list>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>1</hi> By what goes before them: as
<list>
                                             <item>
                                                <hi>1</hi> The word imbraced by faith, <hi>Page 171</hi>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>
                                                <hi>2</hi> Deep humiliation, <hi>Page 172</hi>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>
                                                <hi>3</hi> Selfe-denyall, <hi>Page 174</hi>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>
                                                <hi>4</hi> Comfort &amp; victory, <hi>Page 175</hi>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>
                                                <hi>5</hi> Spirituall ſtrength put forth in duty, <hi>Page 176</hi>
                                             </item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>2</hi> By what accompanieth them: as,
<list>
                                             <item>
                                                <hi>1</hi> Pryzing ordinances, <hi>Page 177</hi>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>
                                                <hi>2</hi> Liberty &amp; boldneſſe with God, <hi>Page 179</hi>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>
                                                <hi>3</hi> And for the moſt part Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans malice, <hi>Page 180</hi>
                                             </item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>3</hi> By what follweth them,
<list>
                                             <item>
                                                <hi>1</hi> More humility, <hi>Page 180</hi>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>
                                                <hi>2</hi> Increaſe of ſpirituall ſtrength, <hi>Page 181</hi>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>
                                                <hi>3</hi> A joyfull expectation of Chriſt. <hi>Page 183</hi>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>
                                                <pb facs="tcp:173875:11"/>
                                                <hi>4</hi> Other degrees of ſealing from the divers degrees of revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Page 185</hi>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>
                                                <hi>Vnto the day of Rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption.</hi>
                                             </item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>§ <hi>3 Of the day of Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption. Page 191</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>From the conſideration of what formerly hath beene ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, ſome generall concluſions are collected, <hi>Page 202</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>I</hi> Concl. Wee may attaine to the knowledge that wee are in the ſtate of grace, <hi>Page 203</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>All that have faith, have not aſſurance, <hi>Page 209</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>II</hi> Concl. Vpon knowledge of our ſtate of grace for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, wee may be aſſured of our future full redemption, <hi>Page 215</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>Why we pray for forgiveneſſe of ſinnes notwithſtanding, <hi>Page 218</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>This aſſurance we have, <hi>Page 221</hi> that, firſt, God may be glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb facs="tcp:173875:12"/>
                                    <hi>222,</hi> ſecondly, our ſoules comforted, <hi>Page 223</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>III</hi> Concl. This aſſured know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is wrought by the Spirit, <hi>Page 224</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>IIII</hi> Concl. The ſealing of the Spirit unto ſalvation, ſhould bee a prevailing argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment not to grieve the Spirit, <hi>Page 228</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>1</hi> To thoſe that are not as yet ſealed. <hi>Page 230</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>2</hi> To thoſe that are ſealed either in a lower, <hi>233.</hi> or high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er worke of ſealing, <hi>236</hi> and that from
<list>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>1</hi> Ingenuity, <hi>Page 237</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>2</hi> Benefit received from the Spirit, <hi>Page 239</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>3</hi> A kinde of neceſsity, <hi>Page 240</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>4</hi> The nature of love, <hi>Page 241</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>5</hi> And other graces, as faith and hope, that worke by aſsimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. <hi>Page 242</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>
                                          <pb facs="tcp:173875:12"/>The doctrine of aſſurance is <hi>
                                             <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                                <desc>•</desc>
                                             </gap>0</hi> doctrine of liberty <hi>Page 243</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>But of deepe and ſweet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                                          <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                             <desc>•</desc>
                                          </gap>agement, <hi>Page 244</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Therefore we ſhould preſerve he worke. <hi>Page 247</hi>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:173875:13"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:173875:13"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Epheſ. 4.30.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>And grieve not the holy Spirit of God, whereby yee are ſealed unto the day of redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether the words bee a Command enſuing from au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, or coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, from wiſedome, or a caveat from Gods care of our ſoules, it is not materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: conſidering both Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell and Caveats of the great God, have both force of a Command, with ſome mixture of the ſweetneſſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:173875:14"/>of love: the Apoſtle as his manner is, from in the large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his Spirit, riſeth from a particular diſſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive from corrupt commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication,<note place="margin">Scope of the words.</note> in the verſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to this generall adviſe of not grieving Gods Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit by ſinne; eſpecially a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt conſcience inlighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: and this diſſwaſive from evill, is inforced from a dangerous effect of grieving the ſpirit of God; and the danger of grieving ariſeth from this, that it is the Spirit of God, and God himſelfe whom we grieve, and a holy Spirit, holy in himſelfe, and holy as the cauſe of all holineſſe in us; and hee that after he hath wrought holineſſe in us, ſealeth and confirmeth us
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:173875:14"/>in that act of grace, untill the day of our glorious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption: ſo that the grounds of not grieving, are from the greatneſſe and goodneſſe of the perſon whom we grieve, and from the greatneſſe and conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the benefits we have by him.<note place="margin">Holy Ghoſt cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Spirit, why.</note> To ſpeake ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the perſon, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit is called a Spirit, not onely by nature, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſpirituall eſſence, but in regard of his perſon and office, he is both breathed from the Father and the Sonne, as proceeding from them both; and by office, breathed into ail that God hath given Chriſt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme, and him to ſanctifie; he is ſo the ſpirit of God in proceeding from God, as
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:173875:15"/>that he is God, which who ſo denieth, deny their owne Baptiſme, being as well Baptized into the name of the Holy Ghoſt, as into the Father and the Sonne; and no leſſe a perſon, then God, is needfull to aſſure our ſoules of Gods love, and to change our nature, being in an oppoſite frame: who can reveale to us the minde of GOD, but the Spirit of God? and herein wee may ſee the joynt forwardneſſe both of the Father and Son and holy Ghoſt; when both Father and Sonne joyne in willingneſſe to ſend ſo great a perſon to apply unto us, and to aſſure us of that great good the Father hath decreed, and the Son performed for us.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:173875:15"/>
               <note place="margin">Holy Spirit.</note>That attribute the Spirit delights in, is that of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which our corrupt nature leaſt delights in,<note place="margin">Holineſſe not onely an attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute in God, but the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of all his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes. He is holy in mercy, in juſtice, in good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp;c.</note> and moſt oppoſeth: holineſſe is the glory and crowne of all other excellencie; without which they are neither good in themſelves, nor comfortable to us. It im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies a freedome from all impuritie, and a perfect ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of it; an abſolute per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of all that is excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent. What is it then to grieve ſuch an holy Spirit; before whom the heavens themſelves are impure, and not onely the Divels trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but the Angels cover their faces? What ſhall wee thinke then of them which doe not onely neglect, but deſpiſe, yea oppoſe this
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:173875:16"/>holineſſe, and indure any thing elſe? what is hated in the world with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eene and perfect hatred, but <hi>holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, without which</hi> yet, <hi>wee ſhall never ſee God,</hi> nor enter into that pure place, into which, we all profeſſe a deſire to enter?<note place="margin">Two de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires in man by nature.</note> There was planted in man by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, a deſire of holineſſe, and a deſire of happineſſe: the deſire of happineſſe is left ſtill in us, but for holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which is the perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the image of God in us, is both loſt, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of it extinguiſhed: and that men might the better drive it out of the world under a forme and ſhew of it; they oppoſe the truth of it, and that with the greater ſucceſſe, becauſe under that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:173875:16"/>great colour the Divell and his Vicar, carry all their divelliſh policies under a ſhew of holineſſe. We ſee in Popery, every thing is holy with them, but that which ſhould be holy, the truth of God, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of it. The man of ſinne himſelfe muſt have no worſe title, then his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe: a ſhew of deviſed holineſſe pleaſeth mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture well enough; as being glorious for appearance, and uſefull for ends. But the truth of it being croſſe to the whole corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man, will never be entertained, untill nature be new moulded by his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit in the uſe of holy meanes, ſanctified by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for that end: it is this
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:173875:17"/>that makes a man a Saint, and civill vertues to be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which rayſeth things that are (otherwiſe) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, to an higher degree of excellency: this is that to a Chriſtian which reaſon is to a man: it gives him a being, and a beauty diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from all other: it makes every action we doe in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to GOD a ſervice, and puts a religious reſpect upon all our actions, dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting them to the higheſt end.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Foure things preſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</note>Now that which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle diſſwades from, is from grieving ſo holy a Spirit. Theſe truths, are preſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: Firſt, that the holy Ghoſt is not in us perſonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as the ſecond Perſon is in Chriſt man,<note place="margin">1 The ſpirit in us.</note> for then the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:173875:17"/>holy Ghoſt, and wee ſhould make one perſon: nor is the holy Ghoſt in us eſſentially only: for ſo he is in all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: nor yet is in us onely by ſtirring up holy moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but hee is in us myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, and as Temples dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to himſelfe: Chriſts humane nature is the firſt temple, wherein the Spirit dwels; and then we become temples by union with him.<note place="margin">Difference of the Spirits be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Chriſt, and in us.</note> The difference betwixt his being in Chriſt &amp; us, is, that the Spirit dwels in Chriſt in a fuller meaſure by reaſon that as a head hee is to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigh ſpirit into all his members. Secondly, the Spirit is in Chriſt intirely without any thing to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: the Spirit alwayes findes ſomething in us, that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:173875:18"/>is not his owne, but ready to croſſe him. Thirdly, the Spirit is in us derivatively from Chriſt, as a fountaine wee receive grace at ſecond hand, anſwerable to grace in him.<note place="margin">How the Spirit was in <hi>Adam</hi> in innocency.</note> The holy Ghoſt was in <hi>Adam</hi> before his fall, immediately; but now hee is in Chriſt, firſt, and then for Chriſt in us, as members of that bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, whereof Chriſt is the head: &amp; it is well for us that he dwels firſt in Chriſt, and then in us: for from this it is that his communion with us is inſeparable, as it is from Chriſt himſelfe, with whom the Spirit makes us one. The holy Spirit dwels in thoſe that are Chriſts af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter another manner then in others in whom hee is in,<note place="margin">How in carnall men.</note> in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:173875:18"/>ſome ſort by common gifts, but in his owne, hee is in them as holy, and as ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king them holy, as the ſoule is in the whole body in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of divers operations; but in the head onely as it underſtandeth, and from thence ruleth the whole body: ſo the holy Ghoſt is in his, in regard of more noble operations, and his perſon is together with his working, though not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally; and though the whole man be the temple of the holy Ghoſt, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſoule eſpecially, and in the ſoule the very Spirit of our mindes, a moſt ſuteable to him being a Spirit. Whence the Apoſtle wiſhes the <hi>grace of Chriſt to be with our Spirits,</hi> the beſt of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:173875:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>delight moſt in the beſt of us, which is our ſpirits: in the Temple the further they went, all was more holy, till they came to the holy of holieſt. So in a Chriſtian the moſt inward part the ſpirit is, as it were the holy of holies,<note place="margin">The holy Ghoſt dwels not in us as in ordinary houſes, but as Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. The holy ſpirit makes all holy, where ever he comes.</note> where incenſe is offered to God continually. What a mercy is this that hee that hath the heaven of heavens to dwell in, will make a dungeon to bee a temple; a priſon to be a para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe; yea an hell to bee an heaven? Next to the love of Chriſt in taking our nature, and dwelling in it; we may wonder at the love of the holy Ghoſt, that will take up his reſidence in ſuch defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſoules.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſed,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:173875:19"/>is that the holy Spirit being in us after hee hath prepared us for an houſe for himſelfe to dwell in,<note place="margin">2 The ſpirit a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor and Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> and to take up his reſt and delight in, hee doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo become unto us a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellour in all our doubts, a Comforter in all diſtreſſes, a Solicitor to all dutie, a guide in the whole courſe of our life, untill wee dwell with him for ever in heaven: unto which his dwelling here in us doth tend: he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth before us as Chriſt did in the pillar of the cloud and fire before the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> into Canaan: being a defence by day, and a direction by night. When we ſinne,<note place="margin">3 We are prone to grieve the Spirit.</note> what doe wee elſe but grieve this guide?</p>
            <p>The third ground is, that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:173875:20"/>we, the beſt of us, are prone to grieve this holy Spirit: what uſe were there elſe of this caveat? wee carry too good a proofe or this in our owne hearts: we have that which is enmitie to the ſpirit within us, ſinne; and an adverſary to the ſpirit &amp; us, Sathan: Theſe joyning together, and having intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and holding corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence, one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſtirre us up to that which grieves this good Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4 We ſhould be carefull of grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it.</note>The fourth thing preſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, is, that we may and ought by Chriſtian care and circumſpection, ſo to walke in an even and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing courſe, that wee ſhall not grievouſly offend the ſpirit, or grieve our owne
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:173875:20"/>ſpirits. We may avoyd ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny laſhes and blowes, and many an heavy day which wee may thanke our ſelves for, and God delighteth in the proſperity of his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and would have us walk in the comforts of the holy Ghoſt, and is grieved when we grieve him: that then hee muſt grieve us to prevent worſe griefe. The due and proper act of a Chriſtian in this life is to pleaſe Chriſt, and to bee comfortable in himſelf, and ſo to bee fitted for all ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>Theſe things premiſed, it is eaſie to conceive the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie of the Apoſtles diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſive from grieving the holy ſpirit. For the better unfolding of which, we will
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:173875:21"/>unfold theſe foure points. Firſt,<note place="margin">Foure points obſerved.</note> what it is to grieve the Spirit. Secondly, is wherein we ſpecially grieve the Spirit. Thirdly, how wee may know when wee have grieved the Spirit Fourthly, what courſe wee ſhould take to prevent this griefe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 What it is to grieve the Spirit.</note>For the firſt: The holy Ghoſt cannot properly be grieved in his owne perſon, becauſe griefe implyes a defect of happineſſe in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering that wee wiſh remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. It implyes a defect in foreſight, to prevent that which may grieve. It im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes paſſion, which is ſoone raiſed up, and ſoone laid downe: GOD is not ſubject to change; it implyes ſome want
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:173875:21"/>of power to remove that which we feele to be a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance: and therefore it is not beſeeming the Majeſtie of the Spirit thus to bee grieved. Wee muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conceive of it as befit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Majeſtie of God, removing in our thoughts all imperfections. Firſt then we are ſayd to grieve God,<note place="margin">Spirit grieved how.</note> when we doe that which is apt of it ſelfe to grieve: as wee are ſaid to deſtroy our weake brother, when wee do that which he taking of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence at, is apt to miſleade him, and ſo to deſtroy him. Secondly, we grieve the Spirit, when wee doe that whereupon the Spirit doth that which grieved perſons doe; that is, retireth and ſheweth diſlike, and returns
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:173875:22"/>griefe againe. Thirdly, though the paſſion of griefe be not in the holy Ghoſt, yet there is in his holy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture a pure diſplicence and hatred of ſinne, with ſuch a degree of abhomination as though it tend not to the deſtruction of the offender, yet to ſharpe correction: ſo that <hi>griefe</hi> is eminently in the <hi>hatred</hi> of God in ſuch a manner as becomes him. Fourthly,<note place="margin">Spirit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidered as in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, as in us.</note> wee may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of the Spirit as hee is in himſelfe in heaven, and as hee dwels and workes in us; as wee may conceive of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as hidden in himſelfe, and as revealed in his Son, and in his word; and as wee may conceive of Chriſt as the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; as incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate:
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:173875:22"/>ſo likewiſe of the holy Ghoſt as in himſelfe, and as in us, God in the perſon of his Sonne: and his Sonne as man, and as Miniſter of Circumciſion, was grieved at the rebellion and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of his owne people. The holy Spirit, as in us grieveth with us, witneſſeth with us, rejoyceth in us, and with us; and the ſpirit in himſelfe, and as hee wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in us hath the ſame name, as the gifts and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and the comforts of the Spirit are called the ſpirit; even as the beames of the Sunne ſhining on the earth are called the Sunne: and when wee let them in, or ſhut them out, wee are ſaid to let in or ſhut out the Sunne. We may grieve the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:173875:23"/>ſpirit, when we grieve him as working grace, and offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring comfort to us: the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Spirit have the name of the Spirit whence they come, as the Spirit of love and wiſedome. Againe, our owne ſpirits, ſo farre as ſanctified, are ſaid to be the Spirit of God: So the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, not in it ſelfe, but in <hi>Noah</hi> did ſtrive with the old world; and ſo we grieve the Spirit, when wee grieve our owne or other mens ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, ſo farre as they are ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified by the Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">How the Spirit worketh in us.</note>Now the ſpirit as in us worketh in us, according to the principles of mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as underſtanding and free creatures, and prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the free manner of working proper to man;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:173875:23"/>and doth not alwaies put forth an abſolute preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive power, but dealeth with us by way of gentle and ſweet motions and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions; and leaveth it in our freedome to imbrace or refuſe theſe inferiour workes of the Spirit: and our hearts tell us it is in our power to entertaine or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject the motions: which when wee doe in our owne apprehenſion, wee churliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offend the ſpirit, as wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to draw us to better waies; and wee cannot o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwaies judge of this, but as grieving. God in his dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with men, puts his cauſe into our ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, that by our prayers and otherwiſe, wee may helpe or hinder him againſt the mighty.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:173875:24"/>And Chriſt puts himſelf into our hands in his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and in the poore counts himſelfe regarde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or neglected in them: ſo the holy Spirit puts as it were his delight and content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in our power, and counts when we entertaine his motions of grace or comfort, we entertain him, and when we refuſe them wee grieve him. And the holy Ghoſt will have us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret our refuſing of his motion, to be a refuſing of him; and not onely a refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of him, but of the Son, and of the Father, whoſe ſpirit he is. Oh, if wee did but conſider how high the ſlighting of a gracious mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion reaches, even to the ſlighting of God himſelfe:
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:173875:24"/>it would move us to give more regard unto them. As we uſe theſe motions. ſo would wee uſe the Spirit himſelfe, if he were in our power. They are not onely the Ambaſſadors, but the royal off-ſpring of the ſpirit in us, and when we offer violence to them, we kill as much as in us lyeth, the roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſeed of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Object.</hi> We intend not in ſin, to grieve the Spirit. <hi>Anſw.</hi> We doe it in the cauſe.</note> 
               <hi>Ob.</hi> It may be objected, when wee doe any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe, we intend not the grieving of the Spirit? It is true, unleſſe we were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels incarnate, we will not purpoſely and directly grieve the Spirit; but when we ſinne, we will the grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of him in the Cauſe. No man hates his owne ſoule, or is in love with
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:173875:25"/>death, yet men will wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly doe that, which i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they hated their own ſouls. and loved death, they could not doe worſe. <hi>Why wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you periſh, you houſe of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael?</hi> ſaith God, they inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded no ſuch matter as peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing: Gods meaning is, why will you go on in ſuch deſtructive courſes, as will end in periſhing? if we could hate hell in the cauſe of it and way to it, as we hate i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in it ſelfe, we would never come there.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 Wherein we grieve the Spirit.</note>For the ſecond point, wherein wee eſpecially grieve the Spirit: griefe ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth either from antipathy and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trariety, or from diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>union of things naturally joyned together. In grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter perſons eſpecially,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:173875:25"/>griefe ariſeth from any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignity offered from neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect or diſreſpect, and moſt of all from unkindeneſſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter favour ſhewed. Thus the holy Ghoſt is grieved by us: what more contrary to holineſſe, then ſinne, which is the thing, and the onely thing that God ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominates, yea, in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell himſelfe? But then adde to the contrarietie in ſinne,<note place="margin">We grieve the Spirit by unkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> the aggravations from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindeneſſe; and this makes it more ſinfull. What grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter indignity can wee of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to the holy Spirit, than to preferre baſe duſt before his motions, leading us to holineſſe and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? what greater unkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, yea, treachery to leave directions of a friend
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:173875:26"/>to follow the counſaile of an enemy? ſuch as when they know Gods will, yet will conſent with fleſh and bloud, like <hi>Balaam,</hi> who was ſwayed by his profit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a cleere diſcovery of Gods will. Wee cannot but make the Spirit of God in us in ſome ſort aſhamed to thinke of our folly; in <hi>lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Fountaine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier.</note> and <hi>dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Ciſternes:</hi> in leaving a true guide, and following the Pirate: men are grieved eſpecially, when they are diſreſpected in their place and office. It is the office of the Spirit to enlighten, to ſoften, to quicken, and to ſanctifie; when wee give content to Sathan, it puts the holy Ghoſt out of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. The office of the holy
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:173875:26"/>Ghoſt is likewiſe to bee a comforter: it cannot there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore but grieve the holy Spirit, when <hi>the conſolations of the Almighty</hi> are either forgotten, or <hi>ſeeme no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi> unto us in the periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our ſpirits; when with <hi>Rachel wee will not bee comforted.</hi> Who in ſtead of wraſtling with GOD by prayer, wrangle with him by cavelling objections: They take pleaſure to move objections, inſtead of a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubmiſſion to higher reaſons that might raiſe them to comfort: and take Satans part againſt the holy Spirit, and their owne ſpirit: and againſt argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that are miniſtred, by thoſe that are more skilfull in the wayes of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:173875:27"/>then themſelves. How little beholding is the holy Spirit to ſuch, who pleaſe themſelves in a ſpirit of oppoſition? and yet ſo ſweet is this holy Spirit, that after long pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, hee overcomes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theſe with his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: and makes them at length with ſhame, lay their hands upon their mouthes, and bee ſilent. Yet that is one reaſon they ſticke ſo long in temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and are kept ſo long under <hi>the Spirit of bondage.</hi> Thoſe likewiſe cannot but grieve the Comforter, that leave his comforts, and ſeeke for other Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: that thinke there is not comfort enough in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but will bowe downe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:173875:27"/>to the world, ſuch as linger after the liberties of the fleſh, after ſtolne waters; as if God kept houſe not good enough for them. It is a great diſparagement to preferre huskes before the proviſion of our fathers houſe, and to dye (like fiſh out of their proper ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) if wee want carnall comforts. But above all, they grieve the Spirit moſt, that have had deepeſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with the Spirit; and have received greateſt favours from the Spirit. When the holy Ghoſt comes in love, and wee have given way to him to enlighten our underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, and when in our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, wee have taſted of the good things of God,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:173875:28"/>that the promiſes are ſweet, and the Goſpell is good. When wee have given ſuch way to the Spirit, then to uſe him unkindely; this grieves the Spirit. Where the holy Ghoſt hath not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet up a light, but given a taſte of heavenly things, and yet wee upon falſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurements will grow to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> diſtaſt, it cannot but grieve the Spirit. And this makes the <hi>ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt</hi> ſo deſperate, becauſe there hath beene a ſtrong conviction and illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.<note place="margin">Aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſinnes of Profeſſors.</note> Therfore of all ſinnes the ſinnes of Profeſſours o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Religion, grieve the Spiri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> moſt; and of all Profeſſor thoſe that have moſt mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of knowledge: becauſe their obligations are dee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:173875:28"/>and their ingagements grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. The deeper dee affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction hath entred, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the griefe muſt needs be in unlooſing. The offence of friends, grieves more than the injuries of ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. And therefore the ſinnes that offend GOD moſt, are committed within the Church; where is the greateſt ſinne of all, the ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt committed, but within the Church? and where there is the greateſt light, and the greateſt meanes. Sinnes againſt knowledge grieve moſt, eſpecially, if there be a malicious oppoſing: for there can be nothing to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe it. The malice of the will maketh the ſinne of the deeper die: and it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the ſpirit, as it is a
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:173875:29"/>Spirit of goodnes, &amp; hence is it that pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptuous ſins ſo much grieve the ſpirit, for by ſuch ſinnes we abuſe the ſweeteſt Attribute of Gods Spirit, his goodneſſe, and be therefore evill becauſe he is good, and turne his grace into wantonneſſe,<note place="margin">Sins a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt knowledg are ſuch either, 1 Directly</note> the ſin of this age. Sins againſt know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge are either ſuch as are 1. Directly againſt know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as when we will not underſtand what wee ſhould doe, becauſe wee will not doe what wee underſtand: ſuch put out the candle, that they may ſinne with the more freedome. This kinde of ignorance doth not free from ſinne, but increaſeth it; ſome men will not heare the Word, nor reade good Bookes, leſt their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:173875:29"/>ſhould bee awaked; this affected ignorance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth the voluntarineſſe. Againe, when we maintaine untruths for any advantage, knowing them to bee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths; as many learned Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts cannot but doe. What a great indignity is it to the Spirit of GOD to <hi>ſell the truth,</hi> which we ſhould <hi>buy,</hi> yea with the loſſe of our lives: and to prefer the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of a baſe man, or ſome gaine to our ſelves before a glorious <hi>beame</hi> of GOD? Other ſinnes if wee know them to be ſinnes, are ſinnes againſt knowledge,<note place="margin">2 Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly,</note> not ſo directly, but collateral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: yet this will bee the chiefe aggravation, when our conſcien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s are once awaked, not ſo much that
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:173875:30"/>we have ſinned, as that wee have ſinned againſt the light, when the will hath nothing to plead for it ſelfe, but it ſelfe; it would, becauſe it would, though it knew the contrary. Involuntari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, takes away ſomething of the hainouſneſſe of ſinne: when there is ignorance, perturbation, or paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, there is leſſe ſinne, and leſſe grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the Spirit: but when there are none of theſe, but a man will ſinne, becauſe he will; accounting it a kinde of ſoveraignty to have his will, this wil prove the moſt miſerable condition: for not to have the will regulated by him that is the chiefeſt good, is the greateſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeneſſe, and will end in deſperation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:173875:30"/>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Why are voluntary ſinnes ſo great, and ſo much grieve the Spirit of God?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Why vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary ſins grieve the Spirit ſo much.</note> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> When there is paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, there is ſome colour for ſinne; as profit, pleaſure, feare to diſpleaſe, &amp;c. When there is ignorance, there is a want of that that might help the underſtanding; but when there are none of theſe, and a man willingly ſinnes, hee is more <hi>directly</hi> carried againſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and will of God: there is nothing puts him on: yet hee accounts it ſo ſmall a matter, that hee will doe it without any provocation, out of a ſlight eſteeme of the good pleaſure and will of God.</p>
            <p>As common ſwearers, can they plead ignorance? they
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:173875:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>know the Commandement, <hi>God will not hold them guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> 
               <hi>that take his name in vaine:</hi> can they plead per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbation? They doe it oft in a bravery, when they are not urged: there is no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement in that ſin of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit or pleaſure, but a volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary ſuperfluity of pride. They would have you to know, that they are men that care not for God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; let God and his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters take it as they will, though I have no pleaſure or proſit by it, yet I wil have my liberty. The heart that hath been thus wicked, will hardly admit of comfort, when it ſtands in neede of it.</p>
            <p>We are not ſaid to be ill, becauſe we know ill, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:173875:31"/>we will and conſent to ill; it is the will that makes up the bargain, ſin were not ſinne elſe. God hath given us the cuſtody of our owne ſoules, and as long as wee keepe the keyes faithfully, and betray not our ſoules to Sathan, ſo long wee poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe our owne ſoules, and our comfort: but when hee ſuggeſts; doe this, or ſpeake this, and wee conſent; hee takes full and free poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of us, as much as in us lies; and God in judgment ſaith Amen to it. God ſaith take him Sathan: ſince hee will not have my Spirit to rule him, it is fit hee ſhould have a worſe. The more willingneſſe, the more ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, and the leſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; and Gods juſtice
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:173875:32"/>cannot better bee ſatisfied than by puniſhing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> againſt their wils, who ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned moſt with their will. The clearer the light is, and the more advantages it hath the more we ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sinnes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſecond Table in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect they grieve moſt.</note>In this reſpect it is, that ſinnes againſt the ſecond Table grieve more then ſinnes againſt the firſt; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe here the conſcience is more awaked. Theſe be ſins againſt a multiplied light, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the light of nature, light of the Word and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: and ſuch ſinnes are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to humane ſociety, they diſſolve thoſe bonds that nature, even by the common reliques it hath left, ſtudies to maintaine. Though corrupt nature hath no good in it, for we deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:173875:32"/>to bee like divels, yet God intending to have ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill ſociety, out of which he uſually gathers his Church, preſerveth in mans nature, an hatred of ſinnes that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow ſociety: ſuch ſins therefore being committed againſt more light, wound more: as in caſe of murther, notorious perjury, theft, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Gods me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod in dealing with ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</note>Therefore God oft gives up men, upon breach of the firſt Table, to breaches of the ſecond, that ſo they may come to more griefe, and ſhame, as being the breakers of both Tables: Men never fall into the breach of the ſecond Table, but upon breach of the firſt: No man deſpiſeth mans Law, but he deſpiſeth Gods
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:173875:33"/>law firſt; No man breake<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>law of nature,</hi> but he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeth the <hi>God of nature.</hi> Prophane Atheiſticall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that glory in the breach of the third Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by ſwearing; GOD meets with them by giving them over to groſſe abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable ſinnes of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Table; which vexeth them more (though they ſhould no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) than ſins againſt the firſt Table, expoſing them, beſides inward griefe, to open ſhame; then God opens Conſcience to tell them, not onely that they are too blame for their groſſe ſinnes, but for the root of them; Atheiſme, prophaneneſſe, looſeneſſe, which are ſinnes againſt the firſt Table. This is an ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravation
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:173875:33"/>of ſinnes againſt knowledge, when our knowledge hath beene hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen and ſtrengthened by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation, by example of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers running into our eyes, which is a more familiar teaching than that of Rule, and ſtrengthened alſo by obſervation and experience of our ſelves; and the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſtrength wee have had, againſt the ſinne wee now commit: and ſweetneſſe we have found in the reſiſting of it. None are worſe than thoſe that have been good, and are naught, and might be good, and will be naught. When there is more delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and fore-knowledge of the dangerous iſſue, and this alſo joyned with the warning of others. As <hi>Reu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ben</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:173875:34"/>ſaid unto the reſt of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> brethren, <hi>Spake I not un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you, &amp;c?</hi> So may Gods Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and conſcience, ſay t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> men, Did not I acquai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you with the danger of ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> You are now in miſery, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> terrours of conſcience, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> did you not ſleight forme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> admonitions, and helps, and meanes? Conſcience is a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> inferiour light of the Spirit to doe things againſt conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, is to doe them againſt the Spirit. God ſpake to me, and I heeded him not, how doth God ſpeake? When conſcience ſpeakes, and ſaith this is good, this is bad then God ſpeakes, conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence hath ſomewhat divine in it: it is a petty god, it ſpeakes from God; eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when the Spirit joynes
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:173875:34"/>with conſcience, then God ſpeakes indeed, then there is light upon light.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Some ſins grieve more than other.</note>Vpon divers reſpects ſome ſinne may grieve more or leſſe than another. As the holy Ghoſt is a Spirit, ſo <hi>ſpirituall ſinnes</hi> grieve moſt; as pride, envy; imprinting upon the ſoule as it were, a character of the contrary ill ſpirit. <hi>Carnall ſinnes,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the ſoule is drowned in delight of the body, may more grieve the ſpirit in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother reſpect; as defiling his Temple, and as taking away ſo much of the ſoule; love and delight, carry the ſoule with them, and the more deeply ſuch ſinnes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the creature, beſides the defilement, the leſſe ſtrength it hath to ſpirituall
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:173875:35"/>duties: grace is ſeated in the powers of nature, now car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſinnes diſable nature: and ſo ſets us in a greater diſtance from grace, as ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away the heart, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4. Hereupon the Apoſtle ſets being <hi>filled with wine,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to being <hi>filled with the Spirit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5.18.</note> And hence it is the Apoſtle forbids, in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer words, <hi>uncleane commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication:</hi> the holy Spirit is a Spirit of truth, hates hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, being painted ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchers; but as a ſpirit of purity, hates ſoule livers, and ſoule-mouth'd ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, as open ſepulchers. They cannot therefore but much grieve the ſpirit, that feed corrupt luſts, and ſtudie to give contentment, and pay tribute, to the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:173875:35"/>fleſh; to which they owe no ſervice and are no debters: and by ſowing to the fleſh from which wee can reape nothing but corruption.<note place="margin">Gal. 6.</note> When our thoughts are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed to content the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man, to contrive for the things of the world one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; this is to pay tribute of the ſtrength and vigour of our affections to the utter e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy of Gods Spirit, and our owne ſoules: when our thoughts runne deeply into earthly things, we become one with them.</p>
            <p>Who will think himſelfe well entertained into an houſe, when there ſhall be entertainement given to his greateſt enemy with him? and ſhall ſee more regard had, and better countenance
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:173875:36"/>ſhewed to his enemy, than to him? when the motions of corrupt nature are more regarded, then the motions of the Spirit. The <hi>wiſedom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of the Spirit <hi>which is from above, is firſt pure,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth us ſo, and rayſeth the ſoule upward to things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove. Chriſtians indeed have their failings; but if true Chriſtian examine himſelfe, his heart will ſay that every day hee intends the glory of God, and the good of the ſtate hee lives in: hee hath a larger hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> than a baſe worldling, that keepes within the ſphere o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> himſelfe; ſpending all his thoughts there, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults onely with fleſh and bloud, with profit and pleaſure, to heare what
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:173875:36"/>they ſay. Such baſeneſſe cannot but grieve the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, as contrary to our hopes, and heavenly calling, which are glorious.</p>
            <p>It is a dangerous grieving of the Spirit, when inſtead of drawing our ſelves to the ſpirit, we will labour to draw the ſpirit to us, and ſtudy the Scriptures, to countenance us in ſome corrupt courſe; and labour to make God of our minde, that wee may goe on with the greater libertie. When men get to themſelves teachers after their owne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſts, as many doe (eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y if they be in place) <hi>Ahab</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hall not want his 400 falſe Prophets. When men cut <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he rule and ſtandard to fit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hemſelves, and not fit
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:173875:37"/>themſelves to it. You have ſome that are reſolved wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to do, and yet will be askin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> counſell, and if they hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an anſwer to their minde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> then they reſt; if not, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their anſwer is: This is you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> judgement, but others a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of a contrary opinion: an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thus they labour to mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Spirit of God in his M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to ſerve their turne ſo did the Iewes in <hi>Ierem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> time.<note place="margin">Jer. 42.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Some will father tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſinfull affections that ari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> from the fleſh, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſtrengthened by Sathan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> upon the holy Spirit, coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting wrath that is kindle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from hell to be fire of hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> zeale comming from hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ven. Thus the enemies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Religion thinke they do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:173875:37"/>God ſervice in their maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres; ſuch are thoſe that wickedly oppoſe the wayes of God, and yet are ready to ſay, <hi>Glory be to the Lord;</hi> ſuch men ſtudy holineſſen in the ſhew, that they may o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow it in the power; and will countenance an ill courſe by Religion.</p>
            <p>Such alſo are faulty who lay the blame of an uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable life upon Religion, when men are therefore un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable, becauſe they are not religious enough. <hi>The wayes of wiſedome are the wayes of pleaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Spirit is grieved by ſinnes againſt the Goſpell.</note>In theſe times, being the ſecond ſpring of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, wee muſt take heed of ſinnes againſt the Goſpell. Benefits, the greater they are, being neglected, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:173875:38"/>bring the greater judgement. The office of the holy Spirit is, by the Miniſtery, to lay open the riches of Chriſt, and the glory of Gods grace in him: by neglecting ſo great ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and by thinking this favour of God to be a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon favour; wee ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, both Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt, and in that they deſire moſt to be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified. Such therefore as ſay to the clouds, Drop not, and to the winds, blow not; and to the <hi>Prophets, prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie not;</hi> that ſtudy to keepe out the light and ſin againſt it, as diſcovering them, and awakening them, and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering them from taking that ſolace in carnall cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the world: as opening
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:173875:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>the eyes of others to know them further than they would be knowne, and ſo to loſe that reſpect they would have in the hearts of men. This cannot but grieve the Spirit of God; and move him to take away that truth that wee are ſo farre from thinking a bleſſing, that wee are weary of it, and fret a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</p>
            <p>The office of the Spirit is to ſet out Chriſt, and the favour, and mercy of God in Chriſt:<note place="margin">Slighting ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> when wee ſlight Chriſt in the Goſpell, the ordinance, &amp; organ of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king good in us, the holy Ghoſt is ſlighted, and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. Bad is our condition by nature, and what a deale of miſery doe wee adde to this bad condition? Are we not
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:173875:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>all the children of wrath? And have we not ſince wee were borne added ſinne un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſinne? Doe we not grow in ſinne as we do in yeares? Is not God juſt? and hell terrible? Now God out of infinite mercy having pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided a way to free us from the danger of ſinne; and not onely ſo, but to advance us to life everlaſting; and that wee ſhould not be ignorant of that he hath done for us, he hath ſet up an ordinance wherin the holy Ghoſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers his love. When wee ſleight this, and account it but an ordinary favour, nay, rather a burthen, and thinke the opening of divine my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, things that may be ſpared; that there is too much preaching, and what
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:173875:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>needs all this adoe? This grieves the Spirit, whoſe office is to lay open the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable riches of Chriſt, thé infinite and glorious mercy, and goodneſſe of God in Chriſt, wherein God hath ſet himſelfe, in all his attributes, to triumph, and be glorified. We grieve all the ſacred Trinity: God the Father is grieved, to ſee his mercy ſlighted: God the Sonne, to ſee his bloud ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted common; and God the holy Ghoſt, whoſe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice it is to diſcover theſe things.<note place="margin">The ſinne of theſe times.</note> This is the common ſinne of the times, and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which threatneth judgement more than any thing elſe. When the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, the bleſſed truth of ſalvation is publiſhed, <hi>The
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:173875:40"/>axe is layd to the root of the tree,</hi> the inſtrument of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: if men ſlight the mercies of God, entertaine not Chriſt, walke not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the Goſpell, they ſhall feele the ſtroke of his ſharpe anger. The bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red horſe followeth the white horſe, <hi>Revel.</hi> 6.4. The white horſe is, the publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Goſpell: when God ſets himſelfe to glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie himſelfe, in mercy, in the greateſt benefits, and wee account them nothing, or but common favours, God removes the Candleſticke; the red horſe of bloud, and deſtruction, followes. And indeed what man will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure his greateſt favours and kindneſſes to be ſleigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:173875:40"/>Now a degree in grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Spirit this way, is, when men will not be tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly conceived of their owne ſinfull condition, and of the infinite love and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God in Chriſt, in the pardoning of them. If God by his Spirit in the Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or in a particular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe come to men, and diſcover their naturall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and tell them they are worſe than they take themſelves to be: they will oppoſe it, and ſtudy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Am I become your enemie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I tell you the truth?</hi> this muſt needs grieve the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">By falſe judgement of things.</note>Againe the holy Spirit is grieved, when yee have a corrupt judgement of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:173875:41"/>things, not weighing them in the right ballance, nor value them according to their worth. When wee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme any knowledge ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than divine know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, any truths but truths that concerne Chriſt, when men looke upon grace as contemptible, and prefer o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things above it, make a tuſh at holineſſe, give us (ſay they) gifts and parts. Alas, what are all gifts and parts, without a gracious heart? Have not the divels greater parts then any man? Are they not called <hi>Daemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> from the largeneſſe of their underſtanding? If parts and gifts were beſt, the divels were better than wee. What an indignity is this to the holy Spirit, to thinke it
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:173875:41"/>better to be accounted wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and politicke, then to be holy, and gracious?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">When we plot and contrive ſinne, the Spirit is grieved.</note> Again, thoſe ſins wherein there is plotting, and contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, exceedingly grieve the Spirit: becauſe they are done in cold bloud. <hi>David</hi> deeply wounded his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and grieved the Spirit, in plotting the death of <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riah,</hi> which was the diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the credit of <hi>David:</hi> that the Scripture ſaith, he was good in all things, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in the matter of <hi>Vriah:</hi> why? becauſe therein he grieved the Spirit moſt, in plotting, and contriving the cruell murther of ſo good a man. How can they thinke they have the Spirit of God, that plot, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine mens eſtates, to have
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:173875:42"/>their wils in unjuſt courſes; or if they have the ſpirit, can this be without grieving it; for the Spirit will perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſuggeſt the contrary.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">And ſinne having helps to doe the contrary.</note>Againe, we grieve the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, when we commit ſuch ſinnes, as we might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void, ſuch ſinnes as we have ſome helps againſt, and leaſt provocation unto. It is a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall rule, <hi>Quanto major fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitas, &amp;c.</hi> The more the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility of not ſinning, the greater the ſinne. Therefore when we are tempted to ſin, conſider what conſcience ſaith: I have beene an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of the word, what hath the Spirit of God revealed and diſcovered unto mee? He hath ſhewed that this is a ſinne: whom do I grieve, by the commiſſion of it? The
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:173875:42"/>Spirit of God, and wound my owne conſcience: and then conſider, will that, that I ſin for, countervaile this? Doe I not buy my ſinne too deare? Sinnes are dearely bought, with the grieving of the Spirit of God: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wiſely thinke before hand what ſinne will coſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">By cavel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt the truth.</note>Men grieve the Spirit, by cavelling againſt the truth. The heathen ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> could ſay, It is an ill cuſtome to be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling againſt Religion, whether in good earneſt, or in jeſt: yet wee have a ſect, a generation of men, that are of all religions, of no religion, men of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictory ſpirit, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes take the oppoſite part; that cavell at the truth to ſhew their parts: this is
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:173875:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>too ordinary among the wits of the world.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Neglect of prayer and depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance.</note>This grieves the holy Spirit alſo, when men take the office of the Spirit from him, that is, when we will doe things in our owne ſtrength, and by our owne light, as if we were gods to our ſelves. Man naturally affects a kinde of divinity (it was the fault of <hi>Adam</hi>) and till God drive him out of himſelfe by his Spirit, and by afflictions, he ſets much by his owne parts, and wit, and thereupon neglects prayer, and dependance on God, as if the Spirit had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to doe with his regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. When men ſet upon actions in the ſtrength of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall parts, perhaps they may goe on in their courſe
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:173875:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>as civill men, but never as Chriſtians, to have comfort of their actions, becauſe they will bee guides, and gods to themſelves. If a man belong to God, God will croſſe him in ſuch wayes, wherein he refuſeth to honour God, and to give him his due place: he ſhall miſcarry, when, perhaps, other men ſhall have ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, though it be to har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den them to deſtruction. This is a ſubtle way, by which Sathan abuſeth men. The life of a Chriſtian is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant on an higher prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciple than himſelfe, to rule and guide him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much worldly buſineſſe.</note>Another way whereby wee commonly grieve the Spirit of God is, when the minde is troubled with a
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:173875:44"/>multitude of buſines; wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſoule is like a mill, where one cannot heare another: the noyſe is ſuch as takes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all entercourſe: It dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth of our reſpect to the holy Spirit, when wee give way to a multitude of buſineſſe: for multitude of buſineſſe, begets multitudes of paſſions and diſtractions; that when Gods Spirit di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates the beſt things, that tend to our comfort, and peace, wee have no time to heed what the Spirit advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth. Therefore we ſhould ſo moderate our occaſions, and affaires, that we may be alwaies ready for good ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions. If a man will be loſt, let him loſe himſelfe in Chriſt, and in the things of heaven: for if wee be
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:173875:44"/>drowned in the world, it wil breed diſcomfort.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Omiſſion of duties.</note>Laſtly, omiſſion, or ſlight performance of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, grieve the Spirit: the Spirit as he comes from the Father, and the Sonne, from God, ſo he is great in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe being God; <hi>Offer this to thy King,</hi> ſaith <hi>Malachy,</hi> when hee ſaw them come negligently and careleſly to the worſhip of God; when people heare drowſily, and receive the Sacrament un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preparedly: this grieves the Spirit, becauſe it comes from irreverence and diſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect: And the reaſon why ſo many are dead hearted, is becauſe they make no conſcience of omiſſions, of drowſineſſe, of negligent cold performances. Such
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:173875:45"/>Chriſtians what doe they differ from carnall men in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>duties, for they will heare, pray, receive Sacraments. He is the beſt Chriſtian that is the moſt reverend Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, the moſt carefull Chriſtian, moſt jealous o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his owne heart. Vſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thoſe are the richeſt in grace. Even amongſt good men, thoſe that are moſt carefull, and watchfull over themſelves: they goe away inriched with the greateſt bleſſing. Therefore let us heare, and ſo heare, let us receive, and receive <hi>Thus, So let us eate of this bread, &amp;c.</hi> The Scripture fixeth a reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend reſpect before duty, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the Majeſtie of the great God, whoſe buſineſſe we are about.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:173875:45"/>
               <note place="margin">The Spirit grieved in others, is grieved by</note> Beſides grieving Gods Spirit in our ſelves, there is an heavy guilt lyes upon us for grieving the Spirit in others, which is done many wayes.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">Neglects.</note> by neglecting the grace of God in them, or deſpiſing them for ſom in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, which love ſhould cover.<note place="margin">Contempt.</note> Contempt is a thing which the nature of man is more impatient of, then of any injury, thoſe that are given this way to wrong o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, are puniſhed with the common hatred of all.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Censures.</note> Wee likewiſe grieve the ſpirit of others, by ſharpe cenſures: and the greater our authority is, the deeper is the griefe, a cenſure infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth: many weake ſpirits cannot enjoy quiet, while
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:173875:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>they are exerciſed with ſuch ſharpeneſſe. They thinke themſelves excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of the hearts of thoſe, in whoſe good liking they deſire to dwell.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">By ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours.</note>Againe, thoſe that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove others, grieve the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of thoſe under them by unjuſt commands: as when Maſters preſſe their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to that which their conſciences cannot digeſt, and ſo make them ſinne, and offer violence to that tender part.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">By inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours.</note>Againe, wee grieve the Spirit of others when thoſe that are inferiour, ſhew themſelves untractable to thoſe above them in magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracie or miniſterie. When they make them ſpend their ſtrength in vaine: thus
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:173875:46"/>the Spirit of God in <hi>Noah</hi> ſtrove with the old world: our duty is therefore, to walke wiſely in regard of others: and if it bee a dutie to pleaſe men in all things lawfull in the way of humanity, much more ought we to pleaſe Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in thoſe things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in wee doe not diſpleaſe God; as being joyned in communion with them in the ſame ſpirit. Yet here wee muſt remember that it is one thing to croſſe the humour, and offend the pride of another; and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to grieve the Spirit in him: no cures can bee wrought without griefe in that kinde, and if wee grieve not their ſpirits, when ſuch humours prevaile in them,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:173875:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>we ſhall grieve our own for neglect of duty.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">By ill ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample the Spirit is grieved.</note>And in the laſt place this cauſeth another griefe when thoſe that are good watch not over their waies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Spirit is grieved for the reproches of religion tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> come from the wicked: for what ſay they? doth religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and the Spirit teach yet this? thus Chriſtians make the name of God to be ill ſpoken of; and this grieves the Spirit, and will grieve them if they belong to God. Oh wretch that I am, that I ſhould open the mouthes of others and grieve the ſpirit of God, not onely in my ſelfe, but in others, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is grieved by mee!</p>
            <p>Scandalous courſes: ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by unreaſonable uſe of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:173875:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>our liberty, without reſpect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the weakeneſſe of others; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r by actions that are in themſelves evill, or of ill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ort; by ſuch actions wee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rieve the ſpirits of others. An ill example alwaies ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her grieveth or infecteth. The ſpirit of <hi>Lot</hi> was grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for the uncleane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation of the Sodomites, which no queſtion haſtened their ruine.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">How it may be knowne when the Spirit is grieved.</note>How ſhall we know when we grieve the Spirit? wee may know that by the ſins before mentioned, as the cauſe of griefe. Againe, the Spirit will bring report of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s owne griefe: wee may know wee have offended a friend when he leaves our company; ſo we may know wee have diſcontented the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:173875:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>Spirit by ſpirituall defen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons, both in reſpect of aſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtance in the performance o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> duties, and reſiſting tempta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tions, and bearing afflicti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ons; as alſo in reſpect o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> comfort, as when wee find a ſtrangeneſſe and dulneſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of diſpoſition; unleſſe it be from ſome naturall diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of body, wee may feare all is not well.</p>
            <p>When wee finde a proune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to divert to other comforts, and to hold cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reſpondency with carnall perſons: and delight not a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> formerly in the communion of Saints, but finde an in dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferency for any acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. When we drive hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and our wheeles fall off; when conſcience will not let us omit good duties,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:173875:48"/>and yet we want the oyle of the Spirit to make us ſtrong and nimble in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of them: whereupon they come not off with that acceptance to God or our owne ſpirits. Theſe indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions ſhew we have not uſed the Spirit well, whom otherwiſe wee ſhould finde a Spirit of ſtrength, a Spirit of comfort, a quickening Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iſſues of grieving the Spirit.</note>The iſſues of grieving the Spirit, will prove very dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous: for the Spirit may juſtly leave us to our owne ſpirits and deceitfull hearts; which as they are arch Flatterers, ſo will prove arch-Traitors to us, and ſo let in a worſe gueſt into our ſoules. The ill Spirit is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ready, preſently to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:173875:49"/>take poſſeſſion; who, by joyning with the ſtreame o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our corruptions, may pleaſe us for a time, but will de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtroy us for ever.</p>
            <p>When we grieve the good Spirit of God, and cauſe him to leave us; our ſoule is left as a hell: for what is hell but the abſence of God, in his favour and mercy?</p>
            <p>Againe, we cannot grieve the Spirit of God in doing any thing againſt it,<note place="margin">Grieving our ſpirits.</note> but it will grieve us againe, and being a ſpirit, may fill our ſpirits with that griefe that may make our conditions a kinde of hell upon earth. Few reprobates feele thoſe terrours here, that the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oft doe by their bold ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures: for beſides the terrours of the naturall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:173875:49"/>they have the Spirit, to ſet them on; and that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that had ſo well deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of them before: which cannot but increaſe the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and ſhame. In hell it ſelfe, this will be the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt torment, to thinke of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing mercy, mercy preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and offered with all love. A careleſſe ſpirit oft proves a <hi>wounded ſpirit,</hi> and that, <hi>who can beare?</hi> and that, <hi>who can beare?</hi> untill hee that woundeth, healeth againe by giving grace to afflict our ſelves, and wait his good time to take pitty of us: that which wee ſay of conſcience, is true; it is our beſt friend, and our worſt enemy. If a mans conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence bee his friend, it will make all friendly to him: it will make God his friend,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:173875:50"/>affliction his friend, nothing can ſit at the heart to grieve him. But if a mans conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence turne his enemy, there need no other enemies be ſought out, he hath enow in his owne heart, his owne tormenting conſcience tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it ſelfe. This may be as truely ſaid of the Spirit of God, who is above Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: if wee make him not our beſt friend, we are ſure to have him our worſt ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, that ſets all other ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies upon us. Diſpleaſure is as the perſon is: <hi>it is a feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full thing to fall into the hands of the living God, who knowes the power of his wrath?</hi> it is a powerfull wrath, no crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath power over the Spirit immediately, but this Spirit of ſpirits, who can fill
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:173875:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>the ſoule, the whole ſoule, and every corner of it, being adaequate to the ſoule, as large as the ſoule, and lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, he can fill it with wrath, of God, when the Spirit of God ſets it on once?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Whence is it that we grieve the Spirit?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe there is a curſed principle in us, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies active, which is not perfectly ſubdued in this life. Death is the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of mortification: but while we are, here, this corruption in us will alway be working. <hi>The fleſh luſteth againſt the Spirit:</hi> the fleſh is an active buſie thing, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtirs it ſelf: now when co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries are ſo neare, as the fleſh
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:173875:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>and Spirit, in the ſame ſoule: they muſt needs thwart and grieve one another continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Queſt</hi> How far a childe of God may grieve the Spirit.</note>It may be emanded how farre forth a childe of God may grieve the Spirit, and yet remaine the childe of God?</p>
            <p>In Anſwer to this,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> know, that wee muſt not judge of ſinne by the matter in which, but by the Spirit, from which ſinne is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. There is no ſinne ſo groſſe, but the Saints of God may fall into it, but yet the childe of God is hindered by a contrary law of the Spirit, from yeelding full conſent before, or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king full delight in a ſinne, or <hi>allowing</hi> or <hi>perſiſting</hi> after. And though in regard of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:173875:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>ingratitude, the ſinne of a godly man admits of agrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter aggravation, than the finne of others: yet ſetting that aſide, the ſinne it ſelfe of a godly man is leſſe, for his temptations be ſtronger, and Sathans malice more eager againſt him, and his reſiſtance of ſinne greater; all which doth abate the hainouſneſſe of the guilt. The more reſiſtance from within, argues a ſtronger party from within, in the godly, the force of ſinne is broken from within: take a godly man at the worſt, there is ſome worke of the Spirit in him, that in ſome meaſure is anſwerable to the counſels and motions of the Spirit without him: the holy Sprit hath ſome hold in
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:173875:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>him, by which hee doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover him. A wicked man proceeds from grieving to quenching, and from quenching to reſiſting. The Spirit hath no party, no ſide in him, and therefore when the Spirit is gone, fare well he: glad they are, that then they can follow their pleaſures and ſinnes without checke.</p>
            <p>Sometimes God leades his children to heaven through ſome to heaven through ſome foule way, by which hee lets them ſee what need they have of waſhing by the bloud and Spirit of Chriſt; which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe perhaps they would not ſo much value, when they grieve the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and the Spirit thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on grieves them, and that
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:173875:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>griefe proves medicinall; the griefe which ſinne breeds, conſumes the ſinne that bred it. We are in cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with ſo wiſe and powerfull a God, that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-rules even ſinne it ſelfe, to ſerve his purpoſe in bringing his to heaven. They have that in them whereby they hate the ſinne they doe, and love the goodneſſe they doe not: whereas others hate the good in ſome reſpects they doe, and love the ill which they dare not commit. Howſoever they are drawn into ſinne, yet they will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver breake their conjugall bond betwist Chriſt and their ſoules, ſo farre as that ſinne ſhould raigne in them as a commanding Lord:
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:173875:53"/>they will not forſake their oath of allegeance to ſerve willingly a contrary King. They may preſume ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times upon Chriſt, thinking they have a Balme ready to cure the wound againe, (as ſome to ſhew the vertue of their oyles, doe make wounds in themſelves) the deceitfulneſſe of ſinne ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing them: but God ever chaſtiſeth this boldneſſe, and taketh ſuch a courſe with them, that it ends in taking the greater ſhame to themſelves; and by ſo much, as they have beene more preſumptuous. The loſſe of comfort, and the ſence of ſorrow they feele, makes them ſay <hi>from experience:</hi> that there is nothing gotten by ſinne, and that it proves bitterneſſe in the end.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:173875:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <note place="margin">Gods children commit not the ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt.</note>Againe, though they are not kept from ſinnes (in ſome ſence) preſumptuous, yet they are alwayes kept from that <hi>great offence.</hi> Though they may commit <hi>a</hi> ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">Since a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the holy Ghoſt, what?</note> yet they can never commit <hi>the</hi> ſinne againſt the holy Spirit, becauſe this is a ſinne of malice after ſtrong con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction: expreſſed in words dipt in malice by a <hi>tongue ſet on fire by hell,</hi> and in actions comming from an oppoſite ſpirit, and tending to oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and to bitter perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if their malice bee not greater then their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. And it ends alwaies in impenitencie, by reaſon they deſpiſe that grace, and caſt away that poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereby they ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover:
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:173875:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>their pride will not ſtoope to Gods way.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, after ſuch feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full relapſes, darkeneſſe in the underſtanding, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion in the will increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, ſinne growes ſtronger, and they weaker and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker to reſiſt.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Sathan being once caſt out by ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of illumination and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, brings <hi>ſeven di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels</hi> after, <hi>worſe than him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe;</hi> when they ſee their former courſes ſtand not with their luſts and hopes, they take a contrary courſe, and ſo fall to bitterneſſe in the end.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Miſcarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt.</note>There is a double miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage about this ſinne: ſome are too head-long in their cenſures of others,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:173875:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>whereas the greater the ſin is,<note place="margin">1 Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing others.</note> the greater caution ſhould be in faſtening it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any, eſpecially whoſe ſpirits we are not thorowly acquainted withall; conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering ſo many thing muſt meet in this ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</note>The ſecond miſcarriage is, in an ungrounded cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of our ſelves: there be three things that feare frees us from the danger of. Firſt,<note place="margin">Fearefrees from three things.</note> feare leſt the time of our converſion be paſt, becauſe we have ſo often grieved the Spirit: whereas if their time were paſt, they would be given up to a careleſſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity. A ſecond is feare of ſome judgement which God ſtirres up in the heart to prevent the judgement that wee may not feele that
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:173875:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>we feare, becauſe feare ſtirs up care, and care ſtirres up diligence to avoid what we feare: a third is, <hi>feare,</hi> leſt we have committed the ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt, which ſhewes wee have not committed that ſinne; it is never committed but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feare, and with delight. In theſe caſes we need feare them leaſt, that feare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves moſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">How to prevent grieving the Spirit.</note>The fourth point is, what courſe wee ſhould take to prevent this grieving of the Sprit.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 Give up our ſelves to the guidance of the Spirit.</note>Let us give up the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our ſoules to the Spirit of God; it is for our ſafety ſo to doe, as being wiſer then our ſelves, who are unable to direct our owne way: it is our libertie
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:173875:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>to bee under a wiſedome and goodneſſe larger then our owne. Let the Spirit thinke in us, deſire in us, pray in us, live in us, doe all in us: labour ever to be in ſuch a frame as we may be fit for the Spirit to worke upon; as <hi>Nazianzen</hi> ſaith of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, <hi>Lord I am an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for thee to touch.</hi> A mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicall inſtrument though in tune ſoundeth nothing, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it bee touched; let us lay our ſelves open to the Spirits touch. Thus Saint <hi>Paul</hi> lived not,<note place="margin">Gal. 2.</note> but Chriſt lived in him: this requires a great deale of ſefle-deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, to put our ſelves thus upon the guidance of the Spirit: but if we knew what enemies wee are to our ſelves, it would be no ſuch
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:173875:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>hard matter.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 To obey him per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly.</note>Secondly, ſtudy to walke perfectly in obeying the Spirit in all things, which requires much circumſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in knowing and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding our wayes: and then we ſhall ſinde the Spirit rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to cloſe with us, and tell us, <hi>This is the way, walke in it:</hi> and upon obedience wee ſhall finde the Spirit incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging us by a ſecret intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that this or that is well done. Thus <hi>Paul</hi> was ſaid to be <hi>bound in Spirit,</hi> the Spirit ſo put him on, that he could not withſtand the motions untill the execution of it. We muſt take eſpeciall heed of ſlighting any motion, as being the Spirits meſſenger, they are Gods Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours ſent to make way for
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:173875:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>God into our hearts, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore give them entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Many men rather then they will be troubled with holy motions, ſtifle them in the birth, as harlots, that to avoid the paine of childe-birth, kill their fruit in the wombe: let us take heed of murthering theſe births of the Spirit. But ſeeing Sathan will oft interrupt good mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions by good motions, that he may hinder both:</p>
            <p>How ſhall we know from whence the motions come?<note place="margin">Queſt.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> How to know the motions of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</note>When two good motions ariſe, ſeeming divers, the Spirit of God carries ſtrong to one, (and that is from God) more than to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Good motions are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther raiſed up in us,<note place="margin">3 They raiſe higher.</note> or ſent unto us, by the Spirit, both
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:173875:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>theſe if they bee raiſed by the Spirit, will carry us to God: they will riſe as high as the Spring is whence they come: what ariſeth from our ſelves, endeth in our ſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 Are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</note>Thoſe motions that the Spirit ſtirs up from within, come from ſanctified judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment &amp; eſtimation of what they are moved to; other motions, are haſty, and gone before they have their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand: holy motions are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, (as ſtrengthened from conſtant grace within) will they ſee the iſſue of what they are moved to: other motions are like lightening, and ſudden flaſhes, that leave the ſoule more da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed then before. Holy motions are anſwerable to
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:173875:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>the duties of our calling: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther motions oft leade us out of the compaſſe of our calling.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3 They change the heart.</note>The Spirit moveth in the godly, firſt by a dwelling in them, and working in them gracious abilities, and then drawes forth thoſe abilities to good actions. But the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit dwelleth not in others, nor produceth any ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed abilities in them, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moveth them ſometimes to good actions, without changing of them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4 Are ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable.</note>The holy Spirits moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are ſeaſonable: other motions oft preſſe upon us, to diſturbe an holy duty. The breath of the Spirit in us is ſuteable to the Spirits breathing in the Scriptures: the ſame Spirit doth not
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:173875:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>breath contrary motions.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">5 Evidence themſelves</note>Motions of the Spirit when they come in favour carry their owne evidence with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as light doth. The motions of the Spirit are ſweet and milde, and leade us gently on; they are not ordinarily violent raptures. Removing the ſoule from it ſelf, but leave in the ſoule a judgement of them, and of other things.</p>
            <p>Againe,<note place="margin">6 Orderly.</note> the Spirit mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth us ſo to duties of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as agree with civill honeſty, and charity to our neighbours. Thoſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore know not what ſpirit they are of, who under a pretence of zeale, will be uncivill, and cruell, ſhewing they are not led by that ſpirit that appeared in the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:173875:58"/>ſhape of a dove. Both Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles in this are one; that they come from one ſpirit: and <hi>the ſecond of like the firſt,</hi> and require love. And becauſe all graces and duties come from the ſame ſpirit, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore one duty never croſſes another; but the wiſedome of the Spirit moves to all holy duties in their ſeverall and ſuteable places.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">7 Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant on God.</note>Motions for the matter good, yet may be carnall, in regard of ſelfe-confidence from whence they come. That which <hi>Peter</hi> reſolved upon was good, but confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in himſelfe marred it: thoſe motions which the Spirit ſtirres up, are carryed along in relying upon aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting grace. So much for that queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:173875:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <note place="margin">3 To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre with the ſpirits motions.</note>Againe, if we would not grieve the Spirit, let us take heed of being wanting to the Spirits direction. The fleſh here will make a fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward objection, <hi>Wee can doe no more then me can.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Spirit is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes before-hand with us, preventing us with ſome knowledge, and ſome abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which if we joyne with the ſpirit in putting forth, the ſpirit is ready to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre with us, and leade us further. And our conſcience will tell us ſo much, that if we doe otherwiſe; it is not for want of preſent aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, or privitie, that the Spirit will deny us ſtrength if we put our ſelves upon if: our own hearts, though de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull, will tell us, that we
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:173875:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>doe what we doe out of wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe; preferring ſome ſeeming good before the motions of the Spirit. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in wee carry in our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that which will quit God, and condemne our ſelves. There is not the worſt man, whoſe heart runnes away from God, but God followes him a great while with ſweet motions, though ſuch bee the invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible ſtubborneſſe of the heart, that it will not yeeld: this will take away all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, as Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> argues well. If I had knowne (ſaith a wicked man) I would not have done thus: ſaith hee, the pride of thy heart ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſts that, hadſt thou not motions and admonitions that told thee the danger of
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:173875:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>it? if the Spirit even in the worſt actions, concurre ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> farre as they are actions and motions; may we not thinke that he is much more ready to concurre with holy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſtir'd up firſt by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe? if the Spirit be willing to concurre in naturall acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, much more in ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, whereunto it ſelfe is the firſt mover; the Spirit leave<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not us, till wee leave the Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4 Cheriſh holy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note>When the Spirit ſuggeſts good motions, turne them preſently into holy reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Is this my duty, and that which tends to my comfort? certainely I will doe it. Let not theſe moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons dye in us. How many holy motions are kindled in hearing the Word, and
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:173875:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>receiving the Sacraments, &amp;c. which dye as ſoone as they are kindled, for want of reſolution? therefore let us not give over till theſe motions be turned into pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes; and thoſe good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes ripened to holy acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that they be not nip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in the bloſſome, but may bring forth perfect fruit. Let us labour to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove theſe talents, to the end for which they are ſent: are they motions of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort? let us uſe them for comfort: are they motions tending to duty? let us make conſcience to doe our duty: let not our deſpairing hearts croſſe the Spirit in his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, nor ſtand out ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornely as enemies againſt our duty, for that is to croſſe
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:173875:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>God, and to nip his motion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the bud.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">5 Give the Spirit ſcope in his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances.</note>Let the Spirit have fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſcope both in the ordinan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces and in the motions ſtir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red up by the ordinances this is the way to make the ordinances and the time glorious; but the liberties of the Goſpell are contrary to the liberties of the fleſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it turneth all things upſide downe, and men out of themſelves. Hence is it tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> there is nothing ſo much oppoſed by the ſpirit of the world, as the purity and power of the Goſpel, which is a ſufficient prejudice of an ill condition that all ſuch men are in. But there is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpirit in gracious men, they are the children of light, and love it. If wee
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:173875:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>would not grieve the Spirit, we muſt be willing to bring our ſelves under all advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of the Spirits work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: as converſing with thoſe that are ſpirituall, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially attending on thoſe ordinances wherein the Spirit breatheth: wherein wee may meet the Spirit. The walkes of Gods Spirit are, in the meanes of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, hearing the Word preached, and holy commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion one with another: the Word &amp; Spirit go together, therefore if we will have the comforts of the Spirit, wee muſt attend upon the Word. Men grieve the Spirit by neglecting the Word, and holy conference, &amp;. It is with the Word and Spirit, as with the veynes and
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:173875:62" rendition="simple:additions"/>arteries: they veynes have ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, that as the veyns car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the bloud, the arteries carry the ſpirits to quicken the bloud. The Word is dead without the Spirit, and therefore attend on the Word; and then wait on the Spirit to quicken the Word; that both Word and Spirit may guide us to life everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting. Motions of this kinde come from the Spirit: as it is ſaid of old <hi>Simeon,</hi> that he came by the motion of the Spirit into the Temple. <hi>Iohn</hi> was in the Spirit on the Lords day: our Manna fals moſt then, Chriſts Spirit and Word dwell together in the heart: therefore the A poſtle uſeth the dwelling of Chriſt in us, and the Word, indefinitely. Faith
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:173875:62" rendition="simple:additions"/>wrought by the Word, layes hold upon Chriſt, and brings him into the ſoule, and keepes him there. It is a bleſſed thing, when the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in the ordinance, and the Spirit in our hearts meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: this is the way to feede and cheriſh the Spirit in us, and to put oyle as it were into the Lampe; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Spirit as it is in us, is thus nouriſhed, even as the fire, though in its owne ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, feedeth upon no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, yet with us here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, it is maintained with fuell, otherwiſe dyeth and goeth out. Take heed of ſlighting any helpe of faith, that God affords us, as wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>Achaz:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſay. 7.</note> GOD offered him for the ſtrengthening of his faith, a ſigne from
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:173875:63"/>heaven, or from earth, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other creature: oh no, hee would not tempt God: hee ſeemed a pious man, hee would not tempt God, but what ſaith the Prophet? <hi>Is it little for you to deſpiſe mee, but you will grieve God?</hi> inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuating, that when wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe thoſe helpes God hath given, wee grieve the Spirit of God. Thoſe that neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the Word and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, what do they deſpiſe, a poore Miniſter? and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect bread &amp; wine? no, they deſpiſe God himſelfe, who knowes better then our ſelves what need wee have of theſe helpes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">If the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſe.</note>Againe, when wee finde the Spirit, not aſſiſting and comforting as in former times, it is fit to ſearch the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:173875:63" rendition="simple:additions"/>cauſe, which we ſhall finde; ſome ſlighting of holy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or the meanes of breeding of them, or yeel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding to ſome corruption which wee are more eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally addicted unto, or ſome ſinne unrepented of, which wee take no notice of. It is good therefore to ſcarce our ſoules to the bottome: there may bee ſome hidden corruption lying in the ſoule, which may under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine our grace &amp; comfort: there may bee a privy thiefe that robs us of all. And beſides beloved and ſecret ſinnes: it is good to bethinke our ſelves of old ſinnes, which perhaps hitherto wee have but outwardly thought of: and God is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling by ſome deadneſſe and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:173875:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>trouble of ſpirit, to minde us of renewing of ſorrow for them: for want of ſtrict accounting with our ſelves, God cals us to theſe arrera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and backe reckonings as wee ſee in <hi>Ioſephs</hi> Brethren. If wee finde not that ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of communion with the Spirit, that formerly we enjoyed, bethinke our ſelves when and wherein wee loſt it, that wee may meete the Spirit againe in theſe waies wherein wee found him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee loſt him, and take heed of thoſe courſes, in the entrance of which we found the Spirit leaving us.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Take heed of leſſer ſinnes.</note>Againe, take heed of lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſinnes, which wee count leſſer ſinnes perhaps than God doth. We weigh ſinne in our owne ballance, and
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:173875:64"/>not in his, whereas no ſinne is to bee accounted little: for if it were once ſet upon the conſcience, and the wrath opened due unto it; It would take all comfort from us. And therefore wee muſt judge of ſinne, as the Spirit doth, if we would not grieve the Spirit; as the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Spirit, is of all the ſweeteſt, ſo the preſerving of it, requires moſt exact watchfulneſſe, and through underſtanding of our ſelves. Take heed of the beginning of ſin, when any luſt ariſeth, pray it downe preſently, ſay nay to it, let it have no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, be preſently humbled, otherwiſe wee are indange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by yeelding to grieve, by grieving to reſiſt, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting to quench, by
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:173875:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>quenching, maliciouſly to oppoſe the Spirit: ſinne hath no bounds, but thoſe which the Spirit puts, whom ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee ſhould not grieve. And let us looke to the head and ſpring of ſinnes,<note place="margin">Looke to the firſt riſe of ſins.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee grieve the Spirit of God, not to the ſinne ſo much, as to the root. Wee are angry with our ſelves for being paſſionate, but what is the cauſe of paſſion? It comes from pride. <hi>Ionas</hi> was a paſſionate man, in that meaſure that he was paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, hee was proud: hee was loth to be ſhamed when hee had ſaid, <hi>Niniveh ſhall bee deſtroyed,</hi> hee thought upon the ſparing of them, hee ſhould bee diſcredited; and he preferred his credit be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the deſtruction of a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:173875:65"/>Citie. So there is much depraving, and detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the world, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon brawles, and breaches. What is the cauſe? a ſpirit of envy, and oft times a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of pride. So men runne into the danger of others, by wronging them, what is the cauſe? worldlineſſe, baſe earthly-mindedneſſe. Men thinke not of the root of ſinne, but dwell upon the act done, wee ſhould be led from the remote ſtreames, to the Spring and ſourſe of all, and bewayle that eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially.</p>
            <p>This care will be helped by ſpirituall wiſedome, whereby wee may diſcerne both wherein we <hi>have</hi> grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Spirit, and wherein for the time to come wee
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:173875:66" rendition="simple:additions"/>may. We cannot maintaine friendſhip in perfect and ſweet termes with any, whoſe diſpoſition we know not, what will pleaſe or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe them; therefore wee ſhould ſtudy the nature and delight of the Spirit, and wherein we are prone both to forget our ſelves and the Spirit. Wee eſteeme not much the friendſhip of thoſe who are ſo much friends to themſelves, as they paſſe not much whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther friends bee contented or diſcontented. The Spirit dwels more largely in that heart that hath emptied it ſelfe of it ſelf: the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> felt not the ſweetneſſe of <hi>Manna,</hi> till they had ſpent their fleſh pots and other proviſion of <hi>Egypt.</hi> The na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:173875:66"/>of Gods Spirit is holy; as it is holy, ſo delighteth onely in holy Temples: thoſe therefore that ſet up any <hi>Idoll of jealouſie</hi> in their ſoules againſt God, that doe not <hi>preſerve their veſſels in holineſſe,</hi> cannot thinke of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny communion with the Spirit. The Spirit is jealous of our affections, and will have nothing ſet up in the heart above God; though the Spirit ſtoopes to dwell in us, yet wee muſt not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the reſpect due to ſo great a Superiour, but reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently entertaine what ever comes from him. Reverence and obedience is the carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age due to a ſuperiour, and where this diſtance is not kept, a breach will follow. Wee ſhould reverence our
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:173875:67" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſelves for the ſpirits ſake, and thinke our ſelves too good for any baſe luſt to lodge in; that heart that the Spirit hath taken for it ſelfe, ſhould turne off all contrary motions with abhominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: what ſhould pride, and envy, and paſſion doe in an heart conſecrated to the ſpirit of meekneſſe and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Renew re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</note>Vpon any breach, wee muſt firſt looke by renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing repentance, and faith in Chriſt, to renew our peace with God, before wee can expect the grace and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the Spirit. For as the Spirit commeth from the Father and the Sonne, and is procured by the death and ſatisfaction of the Son to the Father, without
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:173875:67"/>which, we could never have expected the gift of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: ſo ſtill we muſt have an eye to this ſatisfaction by Chriſt, and reconciliation through it, before wee can recover communion with the Spirit, as being the beſt fruit of the love of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled through Chriſt. We ſee <hi>David</hi> in the 51. Pſalme, firſt importunes God for mercy againe and againe, and then for the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> and for the <hi>joy of ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Avoyd corrupt communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note>And take heede that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing come in, nor goe out of our ſoules that may grieve the Spirit of God: ſome things come in to us that grieve the Spirit; the corruptions wee receive from others: ſome things
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:173875:68"/>come out of our hearts that grieves Gods Spirit, as cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt thoughts, and ſpeeches, that indeed is the ſcope of this place, <hi>Let no corrupt communication come out of your mouthes, &amp;c.</hi> and then fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, <hi>And grieve not the holy Spirit of God.</hi> And after a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine he ſaith, <hi>Let all bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and wrath, and clamour bee laid aſide;</hi> inſinuating that one way of grieving the Spirit, is by ill and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>age. Wee can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e with company that is not ſpirituall, but they will either vexe, and grieve us or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>t, and defile us; unleſſe it bee in ſuch exigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of our calling as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires our converſe with them. But I ſpeake of a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary choyce of ſuch as
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:173875:68" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſavour not good things. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men to pleaſe their owne carnall ſpirits, and the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſpirits of others, they vent that that is againſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and againſt that that is higher then conſcience, a more divine principle, the holy Spirit of God: looſe carnall ſpeakers, are people voyd of the power of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <p>Let no man ſay,<note place="margin">Object.</note> Here is ado indeed, duty upon duty, this will make our life trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome.</p>
            <p>The life of a Chriſtian is an honourable,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, ſweet life; indeed it requires the moſt care, and watchfulneſſe of any life in the world, being the beſt life, it is begun here, and accompliſhed in an everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:173875:69"/>life in heaven. Nothing in this world, neither our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, nor our favour with great perſons, can be preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved without watchfulneſſe: and ſhall wee thinke to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the chiefe happineſſe of our ſoules without it, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo many enemies with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out and within, that labour to draw us into a curſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Motives not to grieve the Spirit.</note>Therefore to ſtirre us up to the practiſe of theſe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that wee may give con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment to ſo ſweet a gueſt, conſider what reaſon we have, to regard the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and his motions, from the good we have by them.</p>
            <p>The holy Spirit of God is our guide: who will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe his guide? A ſweet comfortable guide that
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:173875:69"/>leades us through the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe of this world, as the cloud before the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites, by day, and the pillar of fire by night: ſo hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducts us to the heavenly Canaan; if wee grieve our guide, we cauſe him to leave us to our ſelves. The Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites would not goe a ſteppe further then GOD by his Angell went before them. It is in vaine for us to make toward heaven without our bleſſed guide; wee cannot doe, nor ſpeake, nor thinke any thing that is holy and good, without him: whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is holy, and pious, it growes not in our garden, in our nature, but it is planted by the Spirit.</p>
            <p>There is nothing in the world ſo great and ſweet a
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:173875:70"/>friend that will doe us ſo much good as the Spirit, if we give him entertainment. Indeed he muſt rule, he will have the keyes delivered to him, we muſt ſubmit to his government. And when he is in the heart, hee will ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due by little and little all high thoughts, rebellious riſings, and deſpairing fears. This ſhall be our happineſſe in heaven, when we ſhall be wholly ſpirituall, that <hi>God ſhall be all in all;</hi> wee ſhall be perfectly obedient to the Spirit in our underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, wils, and affections. The Spirit will then dwell largely in us, and will make the roome where hee dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, ſweet, and lightſome, and free, ſubduing whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is contrary; and bring
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:173875:70"/>fulneſſe of peace, and joy, and comfort. And in the meane time in what conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſoever wee are, wee ſhall have ſuteable helpe from the Spirit. Wee are partly fleſh, and partly ſpirit, God is not all in all, the fleſh hath a part in us, wee are often in afflictions, and under clouds. Let us therefore prize our fellowſhip with the Spirit. For are we in darkeneſſe? he is a Spirit of light: Are wee in deadneſſe of ſpirit? he is a Spirit of life: Are wee in a diſconſolate eſtate? hee is a Spirit of conſolation: Are we in perplexity, and know not what to do? he is a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of wiſedome: Are wee troubled with corruptions? Hee is a ſanctifying, a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing, a mortifying Spirit:
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:173875:71"/>in what condition ſoever we are, hee will never leave us, till hee hath raiſed us from the grave, and taken full poſſeſſion of body and ſoule in heaven; hee will prove a comforter, when neither friends, nor riches, nor any thing in the world can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort us. How carefull ſhould wee be to give contentment to this ſweet Spirit of Gods?</p>
            <p>No Chriſtian is ſo happy as the watchfull Chriſtian that is carefull of his duty, and to preſerve his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God: for by entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning him, hee is ſure to have communion with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Sonne. It is the happieſt condition in the world, when the ſoule
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:173875:71"/>is the Temple of the holy Spirit; when the heart is as The holy of holies, where there be prayers, and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes offered to GOD. The ſoule is as it were an holy Arke, the memory like the pot of <hi>Mannah</hi> preſerving heavenly truths. It is an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly condition, a man pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpers to heavenward, when the Spirit of God is with him. You know <hi>Obed-Edom,</hi> when the Arke was in his houſe, all thrived with him: ſo while the Spirit and his motions are entertained by us, wee ſhall bee happy in life, happy in death, happy to eternity. For it is he</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By which you are ſealed to the day of redemption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle ſealeth this
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:173875:72"/>grave admonition by an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument taken from the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits ſealing of them to the day of redemption.</p>
            <p>Wee are all by nature in bondage to ſinne and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption: we are all redeemed from ſinne by the firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt, and are to be redeemed from corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the ſecond.</p>
            <p>There is a day appointed for this glorious worke.</p>
            <p>In the meane time God would have us aſſured of it aforehand.</p>
            <p>This aſſurance is by ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</p>
            <p>And this ſealing is by the Spirit, none eſleneed doe it, no meaner perſon can doe it.</p>
            <p>And what reſpect is due to the Spirit, for doing ſo
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:173875:72"/>gracious a worke, that wee grieve him not; and not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo, but that wee indevour ſo to pleaſe him, as hee may with delight goe on with this bleſſed worke, that it hath pleaſed him to take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him.</p>
            <p>As the duty is ſpirituall, ſo the arguments that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force it are ſpirtuall; and the argument here is fetched from that which hath a moſt conſtraining force; love ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the ſweeteſt fruit of it, and the ſtability of it ſealing, and ſealing to the day of redemption, as if the Apoſtle ſhould reaſon thus; God the Father hath ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned you to ſalvation by the redemption of Chriſt his Sonne, and that you might have the comfort of it in the
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:173875:73"/>way to it againſt all diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements you may meet with; the holy Ghoſt hath aſſured you of it, and ſet his ſeale upon you, as thoſe that are ſet apart for ſo great ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: that the ſence of this love might breed love in you againe, and love breed a care out of ingenuity, not to offend ſo gracious a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:173875:73"/>
               <head>The holy Spirit by which you are ſealed.</head>
               <p>THe holy Ghoſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth to ſpeake in our owne language: we cannot riſe to him, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſtoopeth to us.</p>
               <p>This ſealing is either ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of perſons, or of good things intended to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. Sealing is not onely a witneſſing to us, but a worke upon us, and in us, carrying the Image of him that ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us, whereby we are not onely aſſured of the good
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:173875:74"/>promiſed to us, but fitted for the receiving of it. God prepareth no good for any but whom hee prepares and fits for that good. There is not only an outward autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing of the great grants we have by promiſe, oath, and Sacrament; but an inward, by the ſpirit: perſwading of our intereſt in them, and working that which doth authoriſe us to lay claime unto them after the uſe of a ſeale, both in confirmation and repreſentation, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of him that ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</p>
               <p>The perſons ſealed are firſt Chriſt, and then thoſe that are given to Chriſt Chriſt is ſealed,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">The ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Chriſt.</note>1 By the Father, Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was ordained by him to be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:173875:74" rendition="simple:additions"/>a Saviour in our nature, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinate to be the head of the Church. Wherefore he often ſaith hee came to doe his Fathers will. <hi>Him hath the Father ſealed, Ioh.</hi> 6.27. anointing him, calling him, ſetting him forth, ſanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him by the ſpirit, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very way fitting him with all grace to be a Saviour.</p>
               <p n="2">2 He was ſealed, by the fulneſſe of the Godhead dwelling in fleſh, abaſed, and exalted for us, ſo his fleſh is the fleſh of the Son of God, and his bloud the <hi>bloud of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 Sealed by a teſtimony from heaven of all three Perſons by the <hi>Father,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 20.28.</note> 
                  <hi>This is my welbeloved Son:</hi> by the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> deſcending like a dove: by himself, to his
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:173875:75" rendition="simple:additions"/>humane nature dwelling in all fulneſſe in it. Chriſt is ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by miracles done upon him, &amp; by him, by his bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing and inſtalling into his office, and by giving himſelf up to ſhed his bloud for ſinne, by which bloud the Covenant is eſtabliſhed and ſealed.</p>
               <p n="4">In being juſtified in the ſpirit, being raiſed from the dead,<note place="margin">Rom. 1 4.</note> and <hi>declared thereby to be the Sonne of God mightily with power,</hi> and then advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him to the right hand of God, that through him our faith and truſt might bee in God, 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 1.14. and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing there for ever for us, ſheweth not onely his habilitie and willingneſſe to ſave us, but that it is done already: Wee any ſee all
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:173875:75"/>what ever we can looke for to our ſelves, performed in our head, to our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2 Chriſtians are ſealed.</note>As Chriſt was ſealed and fitted for us, ſo we are ſealed and fitted for Chriſt. There is a privy ſeale in predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, this is knowne onely to God himſelfe: <hi>The Lord knoweth who are his.</hi> And this knowledge of God of us, is carried ſecret,<note place="margin">Simile.</note> as a River under ground, untill his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of, and ſeparating us from the reſt of men. When firſt by his Spirit hee convinceth us of what wee are in our ſelves, and of our curſed condition; and thereby layeth us low by ſorrow and humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation for finne, as the greateſt evill. And then a
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:173875:76" rendition="simple:additions"/>pardon is more to us then a Crowne; then we will wait for mercy, and continue ſo, and begge for mercy, and that upon Chriſts own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, by denying and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing any thing of our owne, then Chriſt is Chriſt unto us. Indeed after this, it pleaſeth Chriſt by his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to open <hi>a doore of hope,</hi> and give ſome hints of mercy, of love; and withall, to raiſe up the ſoule by a ſpirit of Faith, to cloſe with particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar mercy opened and offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Spirit, whereby the ſoule ſealeth to the truth of the promiſe, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. <hi>Hee that beleeveth hath ſet to his ſeale that God is true.</hi> It is ſtrange, that GOD ſhould ſtoope ſo low as to receive
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:173875:76" rendition="simple:additions"/>(as it were) confirmation by our beliefe: but thus GOD condeſcends in the phraſe of Scripture; As wee are ſaid to helpe God, <hi>curſe yee Meroz, becauſe they came not to helpe the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> God ſtoopes to be helped by us, and to have his truth, and power, and goodneſſe ratified, and confirmed by us, when we beleeve the promiſe of God in Chriſt (though it bee by the helpe of the Spirit) wee ſeale Gods truth. And then God honoureth that ſealing of ours, by the ſealing of his Spirit; <hi>After you beleeved, you were ſealed,</hi> ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle; that is, the gracious love of Chriſt was further confirmed to them. GOD honours no grace ſo much as Faiths Why? becauſe it
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:173875:77" rendition="simple:additions"/>honours God moſt of all others; it gives GOD the honour of his mercy, and goodneſſe, and wiſedome, and power, and of his truth; eſpecially hee that beleeves in God, by beleeving ſeales that God is true, and God honours that ſoule againe by ſealing it to the day of redemption: God hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Thoſe that honour mee, I will honour.</hi> Therefore, <hi>Hee that beleeveth, hath the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in himſelfe,</hi> that grace promiſed, belongeth to him, for hee carries in his heart the counterpaine of the promiſes; hee that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth and beleeveth ſhall have mercie. I beleeve, ſaith the ſoule, therefore the promiſe belongs to mee, my faith anſwering Gods
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:173875:77"/>love in the promiſe, witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſo much to mee. The Spirit not onely revealeth Chriſt, and the promiſes in generall, but in attending upon the ordinances by an heavenly light: the ſpirit diſcovers to us our intereſt in particular, and ſaith to the ſoule, God is thy ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and inableth the ſoule to ſay, I am Gods: <hi>I am my beloveds, and my beloved is mine.</hi> Chriſt loved mee, and gave himſelfe for mee. Whence came this voyce of Saint <hi>Paul?</hi> It was the ſtill voyce of the Spirit of GOD; that, together with the generall truth in the Goſpell, diſcovered in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Chriſts love to him. It is not a generall faith that will bring to heaven, but
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:173875:78" rendition="simple:additions"/>there is a ſpeciall worke of the Spirit (in the uſe of means) diſcovering and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the good will of God to us, that hee intends good unto us; and thereupon our hearts are perſwaded to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve in God, and to love God as our God, and Chriſt as our Chriſt.</p>
               <p>This is excellently ſet downe in the ſweet commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of marriage, the Spirit is the <hi>paranymphos,</hi> the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curer of the marriage, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Chriſt and the ſoule. Now it is not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to know that God and Chriſt beare good will to all beleevers (though that be the ground, and generall foundation of all, and a great preparative to the ſpeciall ſealing of the Spirit) but
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:173875:78" rendition="simple:additions"/>then the Spirit comes, and ſaith, Chriſt hath a ſpeciall good will to me, and ſtirres up in mee a liking to him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, to take him upon his owne conditions, with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict of corruptions, with the ſcornes of the world, &amp;c. Whereupon the mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all marriage is made up be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Chriſt and us: this worke is the ſealing of the Spirit.</p>
               <p>Many are the priviledges of a Chriſtian from this his ſealing, as the uſe of a ſeale in mans affaires is manifold.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Seales ſerve for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation and allowance,<note place="margin">1 For con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</note> to that purpoſe meaſures are ſealed: <hi>God is ſaid to ſeale in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. Iob</hi> 33.16. Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation is either by giving ſtrength, or by the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:173875:79" rendition="simple:additions"/>of ſuck as are able to make good what they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe; &amp; alſo willing, which they ſhew by putting to their ſeale, which hath as much ſtrength to confirme him to whom the promiſe is made, as he hath will and power to make it good that hath ingaged himſelfe. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men, there is the writing, and the ſeale to the writing; when the ſeale is added to the writing, there is a perfect ratification: So there are abundance of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious promiſes in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> now when the Spirit comes and ſeals them to the ſoule, then they are ſure to us; the Spirit puts the ſeale to the promiſes.</p>
               <p n="2">2<note place="margin">2 Diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> The uſe of it likewiſe is for diſtinction from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:173875:79" rendition="simple:additions"/>that carry not that mark. So the ſealing of the Spirit diſtinguiſheth a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian from all other men. There is a diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene men, in Gods eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall purpoſe, but that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns not us to meddle with, further then to know it in generall.<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.</note> God <hi>knoweth who are his,</hi> and who are not his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> but in time the holy Spirit diſtinguiſheth, and rankes men, as they were diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed before all worlds, and as they ſhall be at the day of judgement: the <hi>beginning</hi> of <hi>that</hi> diſtinction that ſhall bee afterwards is in this life.</p>
               <p>A ſeale maketh the imapreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of an Image; the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Image uſeth to be in his ſeale: ſo is Gods Image in
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:173875:80"/>his, which deſtroyeth the old<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Image and print that was in us before. Holy and good men by this worke of the Spirit are diſtinguiſhed,</p>
               <p n="1">1 From civill men by the worke of holineſſe, which meere civiil men have not at all, but deſpiſe.</p>
               <p>And ſecondly, from ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming good men, by the depth of that worke, the Spirit of God workes a new nature in them, whereby they are diſtinguiſhed. Now nature in every creature is carried to one thing more then to another. There is a diſtinct propenſion in a good man, to God, to grace and goodneſſe, his aymes, and bent are diſtinct: and thereupon he hath a greater inlargement of heart ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:173875:80"/>to his great aymes; hee looks above the world and worldly men; they are nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, low, baſe ſpirited men, the beſt of them.</p>
               <p>Againe, things by nature worke from within: Herein painted hypocrites are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed from a true ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Chriſtian: he workes from a principle within, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother man is moved as the <hi>Automata,</hi> things of motion,<note place="margin">Simile.</note> Clockes, and the like, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines of wit, that move from a weight without that poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth them: if they doe any good, it is from ſomewhat without that ſwayeth their aymes and ends, and not from an inward principle: nature workes from an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward principle; light things goe upward, and heavie
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:173875:81"/>things downeward, natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: artificiall things are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. Thus good men are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed from thoſe that are ſeemingly holy; there is a new nature wrought in them.</p>
               <p>Againe, nature is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant; what is done natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, is done conſtantly: hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie bodies goe alwayes downeward, and light bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies upward: every crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture works according to his nature, an holy man is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed in holineſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, becauſe hee doth it from an inward principle, from a worke and ſtampe within. Different things may ſeeme the ſame; as wilde hearbs may have the colour and forme of thoſe that are planted in the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:173875:81"/>but there is difference in the vertue of them:<note place="margin">Similie.</note> the ſeeming graces and actions of an hypocrite, they have no vertue in them: as there are some drugges without vertue, dead things. But there is a diſtinguiſhing vertue in the faith of a Chriſtian, whereby he over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the world and his luſts, whereby hee doth all duties, prayes, and heares, and is fruitfull in his con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>verſation; in all his graces, there is a comforting ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thening vertue.<note place="margin">Similie.</note> True gold hath the vertue to comfort and ſtrengthen the heart, that Alchymy gold hath not. True grace hath a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king comforting vertue. Another mans formall arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall actions have no ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:173875:82" rendition="simple:additions"/>in them, neither is it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended; they being only put on to ſerve a turne. Two men may doe the ſame things, and yet there bee a grand difference; the one doing them from the ſeale of the Spirit, from a deeper dye and ſtamp of the Spirit: the other if from the Spirit, yet it is but from a common work at the beſt. Some dyes cannot beare the weather, but alter colour preſently; but there are others that having ſomething that give a deeper tincture will hold. The graces of a true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, hold out in all kinde of weathers, in winter and ſummer, proſperity and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity; when ſuperficiall counterfeit holineſſe, will give out: thus we ſee the
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:173875:82"/>ſeale of the Spirit, ſerves for diſtinction.</p>
               <p>The uſe of a ſeale is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe for appropriation.<note place="margin">3 Appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation.</note> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants uſe to ſeale their wares they would not have others have any right unto.</p>
               <p>A Chriſtian is Gods in a more peculiar manner than others; there is not onely a witneſſe of the Spirit that God is his, but the Spirit workes in him an aſſent to take God againe: there is a mutuall appropriation,<note place="margin">Can. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>I am my beloveds, and my beloved is mine;</hi> when the ſoule can ſay, <hi>thou art my God,</hi> it is not fruſtrate; becauſe God ſaith before, <hi>I am thy ſalvation:</hi> where the Spirit ſeales, God appropriates:<note place="margin">Pſal. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>GOD chooſeth the righteous man to himſelfe.</hi> And wee may
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:173875:83" rendition="simple:additions"/>know this appropriation by appropriating God againe; <hi>Whom have I in heaven but thee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 73.</note> 
                  <hi>and what have I in earth in compariſon of thee?</hi> There is no action that God works upon the ſoule, but there is a reflect action by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to God againe. If God chuſe and love us, we chuſe and love him againe. God appropriates us firſt: wee are his, and wee are Chriſts; wee are Gods, becauſe hee hath given Chriſt for us; we are Chriſts, becauſe hee hath given himſelfe for us; we are, as the Apoſtle ſaith, a people of acquiſition, <hi>A people purchaſed,</hi> purchaſed at a deare rate by the bloud of CHRIST; thoſe that are Chriſts, the Spirit appropriates them:
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:173875:83" rendition="simple:additions"/>this appropriation is by ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</p>
               <p>Againe, we uſe to ſee our ſeale onely upon that wee have ſome eſtimation of;<note place="margin">4 Eſtimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> 
                  <hi>ſet mee as a ſeale,</hi> ſaith the Church in the <hi>Canticles, upon thy right hand,</hi> have mee in thy eye and minde, as a ſpeciall thing thou va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lueſt.</p>
               <p>The witneſſe and worke of the Spirit, ſhewes Gods eſtimation of us: the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is abundant in ſetting forth the great price that God ſets on his children; they are his Children, his Spouſe, his Friends, his Portion, his Treaſure, his Coyne, he ſets his marke, his likeneſſe on them; they are things hallow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d and conſecrated, they are firſt-fruits.
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:173875:84"/>
                  <hi>Iſrael is a holy thing;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ier. 2.3.</note> their titles ſhew the eſteeme that God hath of them; he values them more than all the world beſides, which are as chaffe and droſſe. <hi>The righteous man is more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent than his neighbour.</hi> As there is a difference of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency betweene pretious ſtones, and other common ſtones, betweene fruitfull, and barren trees; ſo there is amongſt men: and in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, God ſets a higher e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme upon ſome, and thence it is that they have thoſe honourable and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous titles in Scripture, of <hi>Sonnes, Heires, Kings,</hi> and <hi>co-heyres with Chriſt:</hi> when others are termed droſſe and dung, and thornes, and have all the baſe termes
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:173875:84"/>that may be.</p>
               <p>Now this eſtimation, by ſealing is knowne to us by the grace God works in us: common gifts and privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, and favours of the world, are no ſeale of Gods eſtimation. If God ſhould give a man kingdomes, and great Monarchies, it ſeales not Gods love to him, at all; but when God makes a man a ſpirituall King to rule o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his baſe luſts, this is a ſeale of Gods valuing him above other men. Therfore we ſhould learne how to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue others, and our ſelves, not by common things that caſt-awayes may have, but by the ſtampe of God ſet on us by the Spirit, which is an argument that God intends to lay us up as
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:173875:85" rendition="simple:additions"/>coyne for another treaſury, for heaven. It is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon grand errour of the times, to be led with falſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences. Many thinke God loves them, becauſe hee ſpares them, and followes them with long patience, and makes them thrive in the world. Alas, are theſe fruits of Gods ſpeciall love? What grace hath hee wrought in thy heart by his Spirit? <hi>hee gives his Spirit to them that pray;</hi> inſinuating, that next the gift of his Son, the greateſt gift is the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, to faſhion and fit us to be members of his Sonne: this is an argument of Gods love and eſteeme.</p>
               <p>Seales likewiſe are uſed for ſecreſie,<note place="margin">5 Secreſie.</note> as in Letters, &amp;c. ſo this ſeale of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:173875:85"/>is a ſecret worke, GOD knoweth who are his, they are onely knowne to him, and to their owne hearts; <hi>The white ſtone is onely knowne to him that hath it,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Revel. 3.</note> and <hi>the hidden Mannah:</hi> none ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly can know the ſtate in grace, as thoſe that have the gracious worke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Holy men in ſome degree are knowne one to another, to make the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saints the ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: there is a great deale of ſpirituall likeneſſe in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, <hi>face anſwereth to face;</hi> that one hath ſtrong confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the ſalvation of another: but the undoubted certainty of a mans eſtate is knowne onely to God, and his owne ſoule: nay, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it is hidden from a
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:173875:86" rendition="simple:additions"/>mans ſelfe; there are ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny infirmities, and abaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and troubles in the world, that this life is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a hidden life in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: <hi>our life is hidde with Chriſtin God:</hi> it is unknowne to the Saints themſelves ſometimes, and the world alway; <hi>they neither know him that begets, nor them that are begotten.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hence likewiſe the uſe of a ſeale,<note place="margin">6 Security.</note> is to ſhew that things ſhould be kept <hi>invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable:</hi> hereupon the Church is as <hi>a ſealed fountain;</hi> ſealing ſhewes care of preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from common annoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance: hereupon likewiſe it is, that ſealing is the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of perſons or things ſealed from hurt. No man will violate a Letter, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:173875:86" rendition="simple:additions"/>it is ſealed: the Tombe where Chriſt was butied, was ſealed, and the Priſon doores upon <hi>Daniel,</hi> that none might meddle with them: ſo the Spirit of God by this worke of ſealing, ſecures Gods children, as the bloud ſprinckled upon the poſts of the doores of the Iſraelites, ſecured them from the deſtroying An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell. In <hi>Ezek.</hi> 9. there was a marke ſet upon thoſe that were to bee perſerved; that ſecured them; and in <hi>Revel</hi> 7. the ſealed ones muſt not be hurt. So where this ſeale of the Spirit is, it is an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument that God meanes to preſerve ſuch a one from eternal deſtruction, and from prevailing dangers in this world. They are Gods
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:173875:87" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſealed ones, no man can hurt them without wrong to God himſelfe, <hi>Touch not mine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed, and doe my Prophets no harme:</hi> And likewiſe from devouring ſinnes, and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous apoſtaſie: a man that is truely ſealed by the Spirit of God, hee never becomes a member of Antichriſt, a ſtigmatized Papiſt (for An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt hath his ſeale too) he is kept from ſoule-murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring errours, he hath this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity upon him by the worke and witneſſe of Gods Spirit. Whatſoever the uſe is, or can be, of a ſeale in mans affaires, that God will have us make uſe of in his heavenly intercourſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt him and us.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="149" facs="tcp:173875:87"/>
                  <hi>Whereby you are ſealed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Degrees of ſealing.</note>Now there are divers degrees of the Spirits ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Faith:<note place="margin">1 Faith.</note> 
                  <hi>Hee that beleeves hath the witneſſe in himſelfe.</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.10. hee carries in his heart the counterpane of all the promiſes. This grace is firſt planted in the heart, and anſwereth to Gods love and purpoſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us of giving eternall life: the ſeale and firſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of election is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted to us in our belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.48. <hi>As many as were ordained to eternall life beleeved.</hi> This belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving is alſo a ſeale to us, in that it is of whoſe gifts that <hi>accompany ſalvation,</hi> of
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:173875:88" rendition="simple:additions"/>which GOD never repents him by calling back againe, it is a <hi>feed that abideth for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">2 Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note>2 The worke of ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying grace upon the heart, is a ſeale, whom the ſpirit ſanctifieth, hee ſaveth. <hi>The Lord knoweth who are his:</hi> but how ſhall wee know it? By this ſeale, <hi>Let every one that nameth the name of the Lord, depart from iniquity:</hi> not onely in heart and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but in converſation, and that ſhall bee a ſeale of his Sonneſhip to him: none are children of God by adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but thoſe that are children alſo by regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: none are heires of heaven, but they are new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne to it. Bleſſed be God the Father of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:173875:88" rendition="simple:additions"/>Chriſt, who hath begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten us a new to an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance immortall, &amp;c. This ſeale of ſanctification leaves upon the ſoule the likeneſſe of Ieſus Chriſt, even grace for grace.</p>
               <p>But becauſe in time of deſertion and temptation we are in a myſt, and cannot reade our owne faith, and our owne graces, it pleaſeth Chriſt after ſome triall and exerciſe to ſhine upon his owne graces in the heart, whereby we may know we beleeve, and know we love: untill which time the heart ſees nothing that is good, and ſeemes to bee nothing but all objections, and doubtings. Wee may bee ſometimes in ſuch a ſtate as <hi>Paul</hi> and his company
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:173875:89" rendition="simple:additions"/>was in the ſhip, <hi>Act.</hi> 27.20. when they ſaw neither Sun nor Starres many dayes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, almoſt paſt all hope. So a Chriſtian may for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny dayes together ſee nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sunne nor Starre, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther light in GODS coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, nor light in his own heart no grace iſſuing from GOD, no grace carrying the ſoule to God, though e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven at that time GOD darts ſome beame through thoſe clouds upon the ſoule: the ſoule againe by a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of faith, ſees ſome light through thoſe thickeſt clouds, enough to keepe the ſoule from utter deſpaire, though not to ſettle it in peace.</p>
               <p>In this darke condition, if they doe as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> and
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:173875:89" rendition="simple:additions"/>his companie did, caſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor even in the dark night of temptation, and pray ſtill for day; God will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, and all ſhall cleere up, wee ſhall ſee light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and light within: the day-ſtarre will ariſe in their hearts.</p>
               <p>Thought by reflecting upon our ſoules we are able to diſcerne a ſpirit of faith, GOD may hide himſelfe from the ſoule in regard of comfort: Nay, a Chriſtian may know himſelfe to bee in the ſtate of grace, and yet bee in an afflicted con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. As in <hi>Iobs</hi> caſe, hee knew his Redeemer lived, and hee reſolved to truſt in him even though hee killed him: hee knew hee was no hypocrite, he knew his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:173875:90" rendition="simple:additions"/>were true: an for all the imputations of his friends, they could not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute him out of his ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; you ſhall not take my uprightneſſe from mee. Yet for the preſent hee ſaw no light from heaven, till it pleaſed GOD to reveale himſelfe in ſpeciall favour to him. There is alwayes peace and joy in beleeving, yet not in that degree which gives the ſoule con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, untill by honouring God in beleeving and wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſtill his good time, hee honoureth us with further ſence of his favour, and powreth forth his Spirit to us, manifeſting his ſpeciall love towards us: and this is a further degree of ſealing of us, confirming us more
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:173875:90" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſtrongly then before.</p>
               <p>The reaſon why wee can neither have grace to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, nor know wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, nor when wee know we beleeve, enjoy comfort without a freſh new act of the Spirit, is becauſe the whole carriage of a ſoule to heaven is above nature, where the Spirit makes a ſtand, we ſtand and can goe no further; wee cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude from right grounds without ſome helpe of the Spirit, ſome doubts, ſome feares will hinder the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to our ſelves, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as thoſe that live in ſome damnable ſinne can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but grant that thoſe that live in ſuch a ſinne ſhall never inherit heaven: and their conſcience tels them
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:173875:91" rendition="simple:additions"/>they live in ſuch a ſinne, yet ſelfe-love blindes them ſo, that they will not conclude againſt themſelves that they ſhall be damned, ſo true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers cannot conclude for themſelves without divine light and helpe.</p>
               <p>It pleaſeth God thus to keepe every degree and act of ſealing in his owne hand, to keep us in a perpetuall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance upon him, and to awe us, that wee ſhould not grieve the Spirit of grace, and cauſe him to ſuſpend either act of grace or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</p>
               <p>Ioy and ſtrong comfort come from a ſuperadded ſeale of the Spirit. The works of the Spirit are of a double kinde: either in us by imprinting ſanctifying
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:173875:91" rendition="simple:additions"/>grace, or upon us, by ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning upon our ſoules in ſweet feelings of joy: what the Spirit worketh in us is more conſtant, as a new na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which is alwayes like it ſelfe, and worketh uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formely: but comfort and joy are of the nature of ſuch priviledges as God vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafeth at one time, and not another, to ſome, and not to others.</p>
               <p>This degree of ſealing in regard of joy hath its degrees likewiſe : ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it is ſo cleare and ſtrong, that the ſoule que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioneth not its ſtate in grace ever after, but paſſeth on in a triumphant manner to that glory it lookes for. Sometimes after this ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, there may bee interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:173875:92" rendition="simple:additions"/>of comfortable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of farre as to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion our condition: yet this calling into queſtion comes not from the Spirit, which where it once witneſſeth for us, never witneſſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, but it is a fruit of the fleſh not fully ſubdued, it is a ſinne it ſelfe, and uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally a fruit of ſome former ſinne. For howſoever wee ſhould not doubt after a former witneſſe of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, yet there will be ſo much weakening the ſence of our aſſurance, as there is yeeld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to any luſt. The know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our eſtate in grace and comfort thereupon, though it may bee weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by neglcd of our watchfulneſſe, yet ſtill it hath the force of an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:173875:92" rendition="simple:additions"/>to aſſure us when the Spirit pleaſeth to direct us to make uſe of it, becauſe Gods love varies not as our feeling doth, and a fit doth not alter a ſtate. The childe in the wombe ſtirres not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, yet it lives, and that may bee gathered from the former ſtirrings.</p>
               <p>This degree of ſealing by way of witneſſe and comfort, is appropriated to the holy Spirit: every perſon in the bleſſed Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie hath their ſeverall worke; the Father chuſeth us, and paſſeth a decree up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the whole ground-work of our ſalvation. The Sonne executeth it to the full. The Spirit applyeth it, and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth our intereſt in it by leading our ſoules to lay
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:173875:93" rendition="simple:additions"/>hold upon him, and by rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing up our ſoules in the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of it, and by breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and cheriſhing ſweet communion with Father and Son, who both of them ſeale us like wiſe by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. This joy &amp; comfort is ſo appropriated to the Spirit, as it carrieth the very name of the Spirit, and is one of the three Witneſſeſ on earth, that witneſſeth not onely Chriſt to bee a Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, but our Saviour. The three witneſſes on earth are the <hi>Spirit, water, and bloud:</hi> for the better conceiving of which place, wee muſt know th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> great worke of Chriſt of redemption and juſtification was typi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in the old Teſtament by bloud; and the great worke of Chriſt of redemption juſtification waſ typi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in the old Teſtament by bloud; and the great
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:173875:93" rendition="simple:additions"/>worke of our ſanctification typified by their waſhing: To anſwer which types, when Chriſts ſide was pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, there came forth both bloud and water, ſhewing that Chriſt came not onely by bloud to juſtifie us, but by water to ſanct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fie us. Hereupon bloud and water have the power to bee wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeſ. The bloud of Chriſt being ſprinckled on the heart by the Spirit, doth pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie the conſcience in aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it that God is pacified by bloud, as <hi>being offered by the eternall Spirit:</hi> this quieting power ſheweth that it was the bloud of God, and ſhed for me in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</p>
               <p>The witneſſe of water is from the power the Spirit
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:173875:94" rendition="simple:additions"/>hath to cleanſe our nature: which no creature can doe but the Spirit of GOD; change of nature is peculiar to the Author of nature. If wee feele therefore our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures altered, and of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle become holy, in ſome meaſure wee may know we are the children of God, as being begotten by the Spirit of Chriſt, conforming us to his owne holineſſe: our ſpirit as ſanctified can wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to us that wee are Chriſts.</p>
               <p>But oft it fals out, that our owne ſpirits, though ſanctified, cannot ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a ſubtill temptation ſtrongly inforced, God ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-addes his owne Spirit: guilt often prevailes over the teſtimony of bloud,
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:173875:94" rendition="simple:additions"/>that of water by reaſon of ſtirring corruptions runneth troubled. Therefore the third the immediate teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the Spirit is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to witneſſe the Fathers love to us, to us in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, ſaying, <hi>I am thy ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, thy ſinnes are pardoned.</hi> And this teſtimony the Word ecchoeth unto, and the heart is ſtirred up, and comforted with joy unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeable. So that both our ſpirits and conſciences, and the ſpirit of Chriſt joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in one ſtrongly, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe our condition in grace, that wee are the ſonnes of God.</p>
               <p>In this threefold teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the order is this; bloud begets water: ſatisfaction by bloud procures the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:173875:95" rendition="simple:additions"/>from God, as a witneſſe of Gods love; and by fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the power of bloud and water, we come to have the Spirit witneſſing, and ſealing our adoption unto us to eſtabliſh us in the ſtate of grace againſt ſtormes of temptation to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. The Spirit petiwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to looke unto bloud, convinceth the heart of the efficacie of it, and then qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eteth the ſoule, which gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth it ſelfe up to Chriſt wholly, and to whole Chriſt: and thence feeles his heart eſtabliſhed againſt carnall reaſon, ſo as hee can and doth oppoſe Chriſts bloud to all the guilt that doth ariſe. And this wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Spirit comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſoule iſ the moſt
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:173875:95" rendition="simple:additions"/>familiar, and affects moſt.</p>
               <p>If wee feele it not (as oft we do not) then riſe upward from want of this joy of ſpirit to water, and ſee what worke we finde of the ſpirit in clenſing our ſoules, and if wee finde theſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not to runne ſo clearely as to diſcerne our conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in them; then goe to the witneſſe of bloud, and let us bathe our ſoules in it, and then we ſhall finde peace in free grace procured by bloud: for oft times a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is driven to that passe, that nothing can comfort him, within, or without him, in heaven or earth, but the free and infinite mercy of GOD, in the bloud of Chriſt, whereon the ſoule relyeth when it feeles no
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:173875:96" rendition="simple:additions"/>comfort, nor joy, of the Spirit, nor ſeeſ no worke of ſanctification: then it muſt reſt on the ſatisfaction wrought by the bloud of Chriſt; when the ſoule can goe to God, and ſay, If wee confeſſe out ſinnes, thou art juſt to forgive them, and the bloud of Chriſt ſhall cleanſe us from all ſinne. Therefore though I feele not inward peace, nor the worke of the Spirit, yet I will caſt my ſelfe upon thy mercy in Chriſt. Hereupon we ſhall in Gods time come to have the witneſſe of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and the Spirit more evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently made cleare unto us.</p>
               <p>The Spirit iſ that wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeſ with bloud, and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeſ with water, and by
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:173875:96" rendition="simple:additions"/>water, whatſoever of Chriſt is applyed unto us, by the Spirit, but beſides witneſſing with theſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, the Spirit hath a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct witneſſe by way of inlarging the ſoule: which joy in the apprehenſion of Gods fatherly love: and Chriſts ſetting the ſoule at libertie. The Spirit doth not alwayes witneſſe unto us our condition by force of argument from ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, but ſometimes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately by way of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; as the ſight of a friend comforts without helpe of diſcourſe: the very joy from ſight prevents the uſe of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
               <p>This teſtimony of the Spirit containeth in it the force of all, word, promiſe,
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:173875:97" rendition="simple:additions"/>oath, ſeale, &amp;c. this is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the promiſe, as a ſeale is more then our hand; &amp; as an oath is more then a mans bare word. The ſame that is ſaid of Godſ oath in compariſon with his bare promiſe, may bee ſaid of this ſealing in compariſon of other teſtimonies. That as G O D was willing more abundantly to cleare to the heires of promiſe their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, hee added an oath, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.18. So for the ſame end hee added this his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit as a ſeale to the promiſe, and to the other teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, Our owne graces in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed if wee were watchfull enough, would ſatisfie us: The fountaine is open as to <hi>Hagar,</hi> but ſhee ſeeth it not, &amp;c. howſoever the Spirit,
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:173875:97" rendition="simple:additions"/>if that commeth, if ſubdueth all doubts.</p>
               <p>As God in his oath and ſwearing joyneth none to himſelfe, but ſweareth by himſelfe: ſo in this witneſſe hee taketh confirm it, but wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth by himſelfe. And hence ariſeth joy unſpeake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and glorious, and peace which paſſeth all underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; for it is an extract of heaven when wee ſee our being in the ſtate of grace, not in the effect only, but as in the breaſt and boſome of God.</p>
               <p>But how ſhall wee know this witneſſe from an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſticall fancie and illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion?<note place="margin">Queſt.</note>
               </p>
               <p>This witneſſe of the Spirit is knowne from<note place="margin">Anſw.</note>
                  <pb n="170" facs="tcp:173875:98" rendition="simple:additions"/>the ſtrong conviction it bringeth with it, which wayeth and over-powers the ſoule to give credit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it. But there be, you will ſay, ſtrong illuſions? True, bring them therefore to ſome rules of diſcerning. Bring all your joy, and peace, and confidence to the Word, they goe both together, as a paire of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentures, one anſwers ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. In Chriſts transfigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration upon the Mount, <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> appeared together with Chriſt. In whatſoever transfiguration and raviſhment, wee cannot finde <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> and Chriſt to meet, that is, if what wee finde in us bee not agreeable to the Scriptures, wee may well ſuſpect it as
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:173875:98" rendition="simple:additions"/>an illuſion.</p>
               <p>That you may know the voyce of the Spirit of God from the carnal confidence of our owne ſpirits, inquire,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 What went before.</item>
                  <item>2 What accompanieth it.</item>
                  <item>3 What followeth after this raviſhing joy.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">1 What go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth before this wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Spirit.</note>1 The Word muſt goe before it, in being aſſented unto by faith, and ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto by anſwerable o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience. <hi>In whom after you beleeved</hi> the word of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, <hi>you were ſealed.</hi> So that if there be not firſt a belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the word of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, there is no ſealing, <hi>The God of peace given you joy In beleeving.</hi> There muſt be a beleeving, a <hi>walking ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Rule,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 6.</note> or elſe no joy nor peace will bee unto
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:173875:99" rendition="simple:additions"/>us. If wee cannot bring the Word and our hearts toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it is not Gods, but Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans ſealing, a groundleſſe preſumption, and it will end in deſpaire: as Chriſt came by water and bloud, ſo doth this teſtimony, it commeth after the other two. Firſt the heart is carried to bloud, and from thence hath quiet: then followeth water, and our nature is waſhed, and changed, and then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth this of the Spirit; though it bee not grounded on their teſtimony, but is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove theirs, yet they goe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Where wee thus finde the worke, wee may know it to bee right by the order of it.</p>
               <p>It commeth after deepe
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:173875:99" rendition="simple:additions"/>humiliation, and abaſement: though wee know our ſelves to bee the children of God in ſome ſuch meaſure, as we would not change our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition for all the world; yet we would have more evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, wee would have fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manifeſtation of Gods countenance towards us, we are not ſatisfied, but waite: After wee have long faſted, and our hearts melted, &amp; ſof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened, then God powreth water upon the dry wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and then it comes to paſſe, through his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and mercy, that hee comforts, and ſatisfies the deſires of the hungry ſoule; GOD will not ſuffer the ſpirit of his children to faile.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="174" facs="tcp:173875:100" rendition="simple:additions"/>3 Likewiſe after ſelfe-denyall in that which is pleaſing to us, it is made up with inward comfort: if this ſelfe-denyall bee from a deſire of nearer commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with GOD, God will not faile them in what they deſire. There are wretches in the world that will deny their ſinfull nature nothing, if they have a diſpoſition to pride, they will bee proud; if they have a luſt to bee rich, to live in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, to follow the vanities of the times, they will doe ſo, they will not ſay nay to corrupt nature in any thing: will God vouchſafe to give any true joy or comfort of ſpirit to ſuch ones? No: thoſe that let looſe their natures without
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:173875:100" rendition="simple:additions"/>a checke, ſhall never taſte of this hidden Manna. But when wee deny our ſelves, deny to heare or ſee that which may feed corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: When wee deny to take delight in that, that wee might if wee would goe the courſe of the world, there is a proportionable mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of joy, and peace, and comfort in a higher kinde made good to the ſoule. GOD is ſo good, wee ſhall loſe nothing for parting with any thing for his ſake.</p>
               <p n="4">4 It is uſually found af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conflict and victory, as a reward. <hi>To him that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Revel. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>will I give to eate of the hidden Manna.</hi> Gods children after ſtrong con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict with ſome temptation
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:173875:101"/>or inward corruption, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, that which accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panieth their diſpoſition and temper, when they have ſo conflicted as that at laſt they get the better, they finde by experience ſweet inlargement of ſpirit: to ſtrive againſt them, is a ſigne of grace; but to get victory over them, even to ſubdue our enemies under us that riſe up againſt us, this bringeth true peace and joy.</p>
               <p n="5">5 After wee have put forth our ſpirituall ſtrength in holy duties, God crownes our indeavours with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of comfort. A Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian that takes paines with his heart, and will not ſerve God with that which coſt him nothing, enjoyes that
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:173875:101" rendition="simple:additions"/>which the ſpirituall ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard wiſhes for, and goes without. God is ſo juſt that thoſe men which have ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to live according to principles of nature, have found contentment propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable to their indeavours; ſome degree of pleaſure attends every good acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as a reward before a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2 What ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, &amp;c.</note>Beſides theſe things that goe before this joy and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, there are ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſome things that doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company it, if it bee right: as,</p>
               <p n="1">1 This ſpirituall comfort inlargeth our hearts to a deſire after an high prizing the ordinances; ſo farre is it from taking us off from a dependance upon them.
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:173875:102"/>In the Word and other meanes it found comfort from GOD, therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights to be meeting GOD ſtill in his owne wayes. The eye of the ſoule is ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſee further into truths, and is inabled more ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to underſtand the things it knew before: as in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the ſame truths that wiſe men underſtand, they underſtood them when they were young, as when they were old, but then more clearely. So all truths are more clearely knowne by this; the Spirit by which wee are ſealed, is the Spirit of illumination, not that it reveales any thing different from the Word, but giveth a more large underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and inward know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:173875:102" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the ſame truths as were knowne before.</p>
               <p n="2">2 A libertie and bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with GOD: for <hi>where the Spirit is, there is</hi> a graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>liberty;</hi> that is, further inlargements from the law, guilt of ſinne, and the feare of the wrath of GOD, that wee can come with ſo me boldneſſe to his throne, and to him as our Father, a free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to open our ſoules in prayer before him. This ſtands not ſo much in mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of words, or formes of expreſſions, but a ſonne-like boldneſſe in our ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches in prayer. The Hypocrite eſpecially in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity, cannot pray, his Conſcience ſtoppes his mouth: but where the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:173875:103" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſealeth, it giveth this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, freely to open and ſpread our caſe before him, and call upon him, yea under the evidence of ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure.</p>
               <p n="3">3 There doth likewiſe ordinarily accompany this ſealing of the Spirit, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans malice and oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; who being caſt from heaven himſelfe, envies this H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aven upon earth in a creature of meaner ranke by crea ion then himſelfe: wee muſt not thinke to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy pure joy here without moleſtation, If there bee danger of exalting above meaſure, wee muſt looke for ſome meſſenger of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than.<note place="margin">3 What fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s witneſſing of the Spirit.</note>
               </p>
               <p>After this witneſſe it leaves the ſoule more hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble:
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:173875:103" rendition="simple:additions"/>none more abaſed in themſelves, then thoſe that have neereſt communion with God; as wee ſee in the Angels that ſtand before God, and cover their faces: ſo <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6. <hi>Iob</hi> after God had manifeſted himſelfe unto him, abhorred himſelfe in duſt and aſhes. It brings with it a greater deſire of ſanctification and heavenly-mindedneſſe. As <hi>Elias</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended up into heaven, his cloake fell by degrees from him: the higher our ſpirits are raiſed, the more wee put off affections to earthly things.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Againe, the end of this further manifeſtation of the Spirit being incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to dutie, or ſuffering in a good cauſe, the ſoule
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:173875:104" rendition="simple:additions"/>by this witneſſe of the Spirit findes increaſe of ſpirituall mettle, it findes it ſelfe ſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led againſt oppoſition. Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt this winde filleth their ſayles, they are carried on a maine, and are frighted with nothing that ſtands in their way. See how the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers triumph upon <hi>the Spirits witneſsing to their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, that they are the ſonnes of God,</hi> Rom. 8.</p>
               <p>GOD uſually reſerveth ſuch comforts for the worſt times,<note place="margin">Pro. 32.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Give wine to thoſe that be of heavy hearts: Proverbs</hi> 31. The ſence of this love of Chriſt is better then wine. This refreſhing <hi>Paul</hi> had in the dungeon, and he ſung at mid-night. After this witneſſing therefore looke for ſome piece of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:173875:104" rendition="simple:additions"/>to doe, or tryall to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe.</p>
               <p>Much muſt bee left to GODS fatherly wiſedome in this, who knowes whom to cheare up, and when, and in what degree, and to what purpoſe and ſervice, and remember alwayes, that theſe inlargements of ſpirit are as occaſionall refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in the way, not daily food to live upon: we main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine our life by faith, not by ſight or feeling. Feaſting is not for every day, except that Feaſt of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience which is continuall: but I ſpeake of grand dayes, and high feaſts: theſe are diſpoſed, as GOD ſeeth cauſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Where this ſealing of the Spirit is, there fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:173875:105" rendition="simple:additions"/>alſo upon it a lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of the head, in thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of our latter end; it makes one thinke of the times to come with joy, as the holy Ghoſt here menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneth the day of redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; as a motive to them to take heed that they did not grieve the Spirit: intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, they ſhould thinke of the day of redemption with a great deale of joy and comfort. The Saints are deſcribed in Scripture to be thoſe that <hi>looke for the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Chriſt:</hi> they are Chriſts, and in him their reckonings and accounts are even. And therefore with delight they can often think and meditate upon the bleſſed times that are to come.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="185" facs="tcp:173875:105" rendition="simple:additions"/>There be divers degrees of ſealing, ariſing from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers degrees of revelation. God firſt reveales his good will in his promiſes to all beleevers; this is the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Church, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in theſe latter times: then by his Spirit reveales thoſe ſaving truths to thoſe that are his by a divine light. So that by argument drawne from the power, they feele from truths in ſearching ſecrets, in caſting downe, in raiſing up, in ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſoule, they can ſeale to them that they are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine.</p>
               <p>The ſame Spirit that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veales the power of the Word to mee, reveales in particular mine owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in all thoſe truths
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:173875:106" rendition="simple:additions"/>upon hearing them. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they are written in my heart, as if they had beene made in particular to me: the comfortable truths in the Word are tranſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed into my heart anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Word; as that GOD in Chriſt is mine, forgiveneſſe mine, grace mine: whereupon adoption in Chriſt is ſealed; which God ſtill ſealeth further to my ſoule by increaſe of comfort, as hee ſeeth cauſe for incouragement. The ſame Spirit that manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in me the word, I heare and reade to bee the truth of God, from the power and efficacie of it: the ſame Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit teacheth to apply it, and in applying of it, ſealeth me.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="187" facs="tcp:173875:106" rendition="simple:additions"/>Therefore wee ought to deſire to bee ſealed by the Spirit, in regard of an holy impreſſion; and then that the holy Spirit would ſhine upon his owne graces, ſo as wee may clearly ſee what is wrought in us above na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and becauſe this is furthered by revealing his love in Chriſt in adoption to us, wee muſt deſire of GOD to vouchſafe the Spirit of Revelation, to reveale the myſteries of his truth unto us; and our portion in them in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar; and ſo our adoption: and in the meane time to wait and attend his good pleaſure in the uſe of all good meanes. Thus wee waiting, God will ſo farre reveale himſelfe in love to
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:173875:107" rendition="simple:additions"/>us, as ſhall aſſure us of his love, and ſtirre up love a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: and the ſame Spirit that is a Spirit of Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, will bee a Spirit of ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, and ſo adoption. Dignity, and fitting qualities ſureable to dignity, go both together.</p>
               <p>In that grand inquirie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout our condition, there is a great miſcarriage, when men will beginne with the firſt worke of the Father in election, then paſſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption by Chriſt: I am Gods, and Chriſt hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed mee; and never thinke of the action of the third perſon in ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is the neereſt action upon the ſoule, as the third perſon himſelfe is neareſt unto us. And ſo
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:173875:107" rendition="simple:additions"/>fetch their firſt riſe where they ſhould ſet up their laſt reſt. Whereas wee ſhould begin our inquirie in the worke of the third perſon, which is next unto us: and then upon good grounds we may know our redemption and election.</p>
               <p>The holy Spirit is both a Spirit of Revelation, and of Sanctification together, as hath beene ſaid: for toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with opening the love of the Father, and the Son, hee fitteth us by grace for communication with them.</p>
               <p>People out of ſelfe-love will have conceits of the Fathers and Sonnes love ſevered from the worke of the Spirit upon their hearts which will prove a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:173875:108" rendition="simple:additions"/>illuſion. Although the whole work of grace by the Spirit ariſe from the Fathers and Sonnes love, witneſſed by the Spirit, yet the proofe of the Fathers love to us in particular, ariſeth from ſome knowledge of the worke of the Spirit: the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour is not in thinking of the Fathers and Sonnes love, but in a ſtrengthening them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by a pleaſing power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe thought of it againſt the worke of grace by the Spirit, which their corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion withſtands. So they will carve out of the worke of the Trinitie what they thinke agreeable to their luſts, whereas otherwiſe if their heart were upright, they would for this very end think of Gods love, and
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:173875:108" rendition="simple:additions"/>Chriſts, to quicken them to duty, and to arme them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt corruption.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To the day of Redemption.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note>There is a double re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption: redemption of the ſoule by the firſt comming of Chriſt, to ſhed his bloud for us; redemption of our bodies from corruption, by his ſecond comming. Wee have not the perfect con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummation and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of that which Chriſt wrought in his firſt comming, till his ſecond comming, then there ſhall bee a totall redemption of our ſoules and bodies, and conditions. There is a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble redemption, as there is
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:173875:109" rendition="simple:additions"/>a double co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of Chriſt; the firſt, and the ſecond; the one to redeeme our ſoules from ſinne and Sathan, and to give us title to heaven, the other to redeeme our bodies from corruption, when <hi>Chriſt ſhall come to bee glorious in his Saints.</hi> As likewiſe there is a double reſurrection, the firſt and the ſecond, and a double re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation of ſoule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</p>
               <p>In ſickneſſe &amp; weaknes of body, or when age hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertaken us, that we cannot live long here, and the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of the grave, the houſe of darkeneſſe, is preſented to us. Oh let us thinke, there will bee a redemption of our bodies, as well as of our ſoules! Chriſt will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:173875:109" rendition="simple:additions"/>our bodies from cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, as he came to work the redemption of our ſoules from ſinne and death; and hee that will redeeme our bodies out of the grave, he will redeeme his Church out of miſery, hee will call the Iewes; hee that will doe the greater, will doe the inferiour. When wee heare of this, let us thinke with comfort of all the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that are yet unperfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption not yet.</note>Secondly, full redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption is not yet, What need I bring Scripture to prove it? It is a point that every mans experience teacheth. Alas, let our bodies ſpeake<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wee are not free from ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and diſeaſes: nay, what is our life but a going
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:173875:110"/>to corruption? the ſentence is paſſed upon us, <hi>earth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneth to earth;</hi> till death wee are going to death, ſo beſides ſickneſſe and weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe here, we muſt dye, and after death bee ſubject to corruption. The Apoſtle in this reſpect calleth our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, <hi>a vile body.</hi> As for our ſoules, though they bee freed from the guilt and damnation of ſinne, yet there are remainders of corruption that breed feare and terrour; and though they be freed from the rule of Sathan, yet not from his moleſtation and vexations by temptations. In a word, our whole ſtate and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in this world, is a ſtate and condition of miſery, wee are followed with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:173875:110" rendition="simple:additions"/>afflictions, ſo that there is not yet perfect redemption, whether we looke to body, ſoule, or ſtate; the body be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſubject to diſeaſes, the ſoule to infirmities, the ſtate to miſery.</p>
               <p>But there is a <hi>day</hi> appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A day of Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note>By a <hi>day</hi> wee are not to underſtand the time meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the courſe of the Sunne in 24 houres, but in the Scriptures meaning, a day is a ſet time of mercy or judgement. As there was a ſolemne day, <hi>the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of time,</hi> for the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the firſt redemption, ſo there is a ſolemn time ſet for the ſecond redemption, when all the children of God ſhall bee gathered; thoſe that lye in the duſt
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:173875:111"/>ſhall be raiſed, and for ever glorified. It is the day of all dayes: that day that by way of excellency, is called <hi>THAT day</hi> in the Scriptures, and <hi>the day of the Lord.</hi> The day that were ſhould thinke of every day; eſpecially in ſickneſſe and trouble, and croſſes, and moleſtations, from the wicked world, and in ſenſe of the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of corruption. There is a day of redemption to come, that will make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends for all. The fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent thoughts of that day would comfort us, and keepe us from ſhrinking in any affliction and trouble; it would move us to a carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age and converſation an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to our hopes, and alſo it would helpe to fit us;
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:173875:111"/>it would infuſe a deſire of qualification to be prepared for that great day.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The day of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption ought to be thought on.</note>But how little of our time is ſpent in thoughts this way? If wee could oft thinke of the day of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, our lives would bee otherwiſe, both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of gracious, as alſo of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable carriage, ſhould we be diſconſolate at every loſſe and croſſe, at ſickneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and the thought of death, when wee ſhall be turned into our firſt princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the earth? if wee did thinke of the day of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, when all ſhall be reſtored againe, all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayes of nature, and the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God be perfectly ſtamped: the thought of this would make us goe wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:173875:112" rendition="simple:additions"/>to our graves, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that all this is but a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration for the great <hi>day of redemption</hi> The firſt day of redemption, when Chriſt came to redeeme our ſoules, and to give us title to heaven; It was in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of all good people before Chriſt; they are ſaid <hi>to wait for the conſolation of Iſrael;</hi> that was the chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter to know thoſe bleſſed people by. And what ſhould be the diſtinguiſhing character of gracious ſoules now, but to bee ſuch as wait for the comming of Chriſt? how oft in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> is it? <hi>There is a Crowne of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for mee, and for all that wait for the appearing of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="199" facs="tcp:173875:112" rendition="simple:additions"/>There was a yeare of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile</hi> among the Iewes eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fifty yeares; then all that were in bondage were ſet at liberty. So at this bleſſed <hi>Iubile,</hi> this glorious day of redemption, all that are in bondage of death, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der corruption, ſhall be ſet at everlaſting liberty. No queſtion but the poore ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants that were vexed with hard maſters, they thought of the Iubile, and thoſe that had their poſſeſſions tooke away, they thought of the Iubile, the day of recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all. So let us oft thinke of this everlaſting Iubile, when wee ſhall recover all that wee loſt, for ever to keepe it, and never to loſe it againe as wee did in the firſt creation. Let us oft
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:173875:113" rendition="simple:additions"/>thinke of this day; it will infuſe vigour and ſtrength into all our converſation. Indeed to the ungodly, it is not a day of <hi>redemption,</hi> but a day of <hi>judgement,</hi> and <hi>the revelation of the juſt wrath of God,</hi> when their ſins ſhall be laid open, and receive a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence anſwerable.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Day of vengeance to wicked.</note>Alas, there is ſuch a deale of Atheiſme in the world, (and the ſeeds of it in the beſt, unleſſe it be wrought out daily) that we forget the God of vengeance, and the day of vengeance. Would men goe on in ſinnes againſt conſcience, if they thought of this laſt day? It is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible: ſuch courſes come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this abhominable root of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme, and unbeliefe, for had they but a ſlight Faith,
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:173875:113"/>it would be effectual to alter their courſe in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: therefore the Scripture gives them the name of fooles (though they would be thought to bee the onely wiſe men.) <hi>The foole hath ſaid in his heart, there is no God:</hi> and what followes? <hi>Corrupt are they, and abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable.</hi> The cauſe of all is, the foole hath ſaid in his heart, he will needs force it upon his heart; that there is no God, hell nor heaven, nor judgement; thence come abhominable cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="202" facs="tcp:173875:114"/>
               <head>Grieve not the holy Spirit of God, whereby yee are ſealed unto the day of Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption.</head>
               <p>FRom the conſideration of all that hath beene formerly ſpoken of, the ſealing of the ſpirit to the day of Redemption, there ariſeth theſe foure concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that we may attaine unto to knowledge that wee are in that ſtate of grace.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that upon know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our ſtate in grace for the preſent, we may be aſſured of our future ful Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that this aſſured knowledge is wrought by the Spirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="203" facs="tcp:173875:114" rendition="simple:additions"/>Fourthly, that the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of this aſſurance wrought by the Spirit, is an effectuall argument to diſſwade from grieving the Spirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The firſt concluſion.</note>For the firſt <hi>wee may know wee are in the ſtate of grace:</hi> firſt, becauſe the Apoſtle would not have uſed an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument moving, not to grieve the Spirit, from a thing unknowne or gueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at; it is an ill manner of reaſoning to argue from a thing unknowne.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Againe, ſealing of us by the Spirit, is not in regard of God, but of our ſelves. God knoweth who are his, but we know not that weare his, but by ſealing.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The ſcope of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures indited by the Spirit,
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:173875:115" rendition="simple:additions"/>is for comfort, the Apoſtle ſaith ſo directly, and what comfort in an uncertaine condition, wherein a man knowes not but hee may be a reprobate? Wherefore came our Saviour into the world, and tooke our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture upon him; why became he a curſe for us; why hath hee carried our nature into heaven, and there appeares for us till hee hath brought us home to himſelfe, but that hee would have us out of all doubt of his love af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter once by faith wee have received him? whence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded thoſe Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements to beleeve, thoſe checkes of unbeleevers, the commendation of them that did beleeve, thoſe upbraidings of doubting,
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:173875:115" rendition="simple:additions"/>as ſpringing from unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe: to what uſe are the Sacraments, but to ſeale un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us the benefits of Chriſt? if upon all this wee ſhould ſtill doubt of GODS love, eſpecially when be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the ſealing of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes to us, wee are ſealed our ſelves by the Spirit of promiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> This is true, if wee know we doe beleeve:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> It is the office of the Spirit, as to worke Faith and other graces, ſo to reveale them to us: every grace of GOD is a light of it ſelfe, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from the Father of lights: and it is the proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of light, not onely to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover other things, but it ſelfe too; and it is the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:173875:116" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the Spirit to give further light to this light by ſhining upon his owne grace in us: an excellent place for this is the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Wee have received the Spirit that is of God, that wee might know the things that are freely given to us of God,</hi> in the mouth of two or three witneſſes ſhall every thing bee confirmed: one witneſſes is <hi>the Spirit of man</hi> which knowes <hi>the things that are in man;</hi> the other witneſſes is <hi>the Spirit of God, witneſsing to our ſpirits that we are the children of God.</hi> Here is light added to light, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe added to witneſſe, the greater witneſſe of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to the leſſe of our Spirits: the Apoſtle joynes them both together,<note place="margin">Rom. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>My conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:173875:116" rendition="simple:additions"/>bears me witneſſe through the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obje.</hi> Mans heart is deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> But the ſpirit of God in mans heart is not deceitfull, it is too holy to deceive, and too wiſe to be deceived in this point of aſſurance: wee plow with the Spirits Heifer, or elſe we could not finde out this Riddle: where there is an object to be ſeene, and an eye to ſee, and light to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the object to the eye, ſight muſt needs follow. In a true beleever, after he is inlightened, as there is grace to bee ſeene, and an eye of Faith to ſee, ſo there is a light of the Spirit diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering that grace to that inward ſight: in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:173875:117" rendition="simple:additions"/>of a cleare River, a cleare eye ſight may ſee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing; where nothing is, nothing can bee ſeene; it is an evidence that the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons of doubtings have lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle grace in them, and much boldneſſe in making themſelves a meaſure for other. Thoſe that are baſe borne, know their Mothers better then their Fathers;<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.</note> the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is all for the Mother, but the babes of Chriſt know their Father; the remainder of corruption will indeed be ſtill breeding doubts, but it is the office of the Spirit of Faith to quell them as they ariſe. Wee are too rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in time of temptation to doubt, wee need not helpe the tempter, by holding it
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:173875:117" rendition="simple:additions"/>a duty to doubt; this is to light a candle before the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell as we uſe to ſpeake.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi> May not there be doubtings where there is true faith, may not a true beleever bee without aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance?</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> There bee three rankes of Chriſtians: firſt, ſome that are yet under the ſpirit of bondage, that like little children doe all for feare. Secondly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> thoſe that are under the ſpirit of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption, and doe many things well, but yet are not altogether free from feare; theſe are like thoſe chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren that are moved with reverence to obey their Parents, and yet finde their commands ſomewhat irke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome unto them.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:173875:118" rendition="simple:additions"/>are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>h as by the love of God ſhed into the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> hearts by the Spirit of adoption, are carried with large Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits to obey their father, and herein like unto thoſe children, that not onely o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey, but take a delight in it upon a judgement that both obedience and the thing wherein they obey is good; this wee ought to labour for, but wee finde many Chriſtians in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ranke, many truely beleeve in Chriſt by ſome light let into their hearts by the Spirit of adoption, who are not yet fully aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the love of Chriſt. There is the act of faith, and the fruit of Faith; the act of faith is to caſt our ſelves upon Gods mercy
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:173875:118" rendition="simple:additions"/>in Chriſt, the fruit of faith is in beleeving to bee aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of this: wee muſt know that faith is one thing, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance another, they may have faith, and yet want a double aſſurance: firſt, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of their faith, being not able to judge at all times of their owne act; likewiſe, ſecondly, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of their ſtate in grace, as in time of deſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and temptation: a ſoule at ſuch a time caſts it ſelfe upon Chriſt, as knowing comfort is there to be had, though hee bee not ſure of it for himſelfe: and this the ſoule doth out of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, though not out of feeling, as the poore man in the Goſpell, <hi>Lord I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, helpe my unbeliefe:</hi>
                  <pb n="212" facs="tcp:173875:119" rendition="simple:additions"/>the ſoule often times out of the deepe, cryes, and in the darke truſts in GOD, and this is the bold adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of faith, the firſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject whereof is <hi>Chriſt</hi> held out in a promiſe; and not <hi>aſſurance,</hi> which ſpringeth from the firſt act when it pleaſeth God to ſhine up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſoule, and is a reward of glorifying Gods mercy in Chriſt by caſting the ſoule upon his truth and goodneſſe. Aſſurance is GODS ſeale, faith is our ſeale; when wee ſet to our ſeale by beleeving, hee ſets to his ſeale, aſſuring us of our condition: we yeeld firſt the conſent and the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of faith, and then God puts his ſeale to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract: there muſt be a good
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:173875:119"/>title before a confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a planting before a roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and eſtabliſhing, the bargaine before the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt. Some would have Faith to bee an over-pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring light of the ſoule, whereby undoubtedly they beleeve themſelves to bee Chriſt, and Chriſt to be theirs: which ſtumbleth many a weake, yet true Chriſtian, for this is rather the fruit of a ſtrong Faith, then the act of a weake, which ſtruggleth with doubting, untill it hath gotten the upper hand. True it is, there muſt bee ſo much light let in to the ſoule, as the ſoule may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon Chriſt, and this light muſt bee diſcovered by the Spirit, and ſuch a
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:173875:120"/>light as ſhewes a ſpeciall love of Chriſt to the ſoule. And againe, it is true that wee are not to take up our reſt in the light, untill the heart be further ſubdued: as many are too haſty to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude of a good condition upon uncertaine ſignes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they have attained un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to fuller aſſurance, but yet wee muſt not deny faith where this ſtrong aſſurance is wanting, ſo farre as to conclude againſt our ſelves; if there be deſires, putting on, to endeavour with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict againſt the riſing of unbeliefe, with a high pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the favour of God in Chriſt, ſo as to value it above all things. Degrees doe not varie the kinde, weakeneſſe may ſtand with
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:173875:120"/>truth; but where truth is, there will be an unceſſant deſire of future ſealing.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.</note>The ſecond concluſion: <hi>We may upon the knowledge of our preſent eſtate in grace bee aſſured for the time to come:</hi> for this ſealing is to the day of Redemption; that is, till wee be put into full poſſeſſion of what we now beleeve; and beſides, ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is for ſecuring for the time to come, and our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours promiſe is, that though He departed from them, yet the Comforter ſhould abide with them for ever, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14. And why are wee certaine of the favour of God to our comfort for the preſent, but that wee doubt not of it for the time to come?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="216" facs="tcp:173875:121" rendition="simple:additions"/>Faith and love, and theſe graces, they never faile fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally; therefore when the Scripture ſpeakes of Faith, it ſpeakes of ſalvation by it for the preſent: as if a man ſhould bee in heaven pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſo ſoone as hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeves. <hi>Wee are ſaved by faith,</hi> ſay the Scriptures: we are not yet ſaved; but the meaning is, wee are<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſet by faith into a ſtate of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. Being put into Chriſt by Faith, we <hi>are ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen with Chriſt, and ſit in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly places with him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Col. 2.</note> Faith makes the things to come, preſent: and Faith beleeves, that <hi>neither things preſent, nor things to come,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> ſhall bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſeparate us from the love of God in Chriſt.</hi> So that our aſſurance is not onely
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:173875:121"/>for the preſent, but for the time to come. We are ſealed <hi>to the day of Redemption,</hi> and who can reverſe Gods ſeale, or Gods act &amp; deed? Grace is the earneſt penny of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: God hath made a cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and given earneſt, hee will not loſe it, the earneſt is never taken away, but filled up; if we be aſſured of grace for the preſent, wee may bee ſure it ſhall bee made up full in glory hereafter. If the ſpirit of Chriſt bee in us, the ſame ſpirit that raiſed Chriſt from the dead, will raiſe us up likewiſe,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.11</note> and not leave us untill wee bee in full redemption, <hi>wee ſhall walke, filled with his i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal.</note>
               </p>
               <p>No oppoſition ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile, God hath ſet us as a
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:173875:122" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſeale on his right hand to keep us, I and on his breaſt (as the high Prieſt had the twelve Tribes) to love us, and on his ſhoulder to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port us. The marked and ſealed ones in <hi>Ezech.</hi> 9. and <hi>Rev.</hi> 7. were ſecured from all deſtruction. If we be in Chriſt our Rocke, temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and oppoſitions are but as waves, they may daſh upon <hi>us,</hi> but they breake <hi>themſelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why then doe we pray for the forgiveneſſe of ſinnes?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Why wee pray for forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinnes.</note> 
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Wee pray for a clearer evidence of what wee have: ſecondly, as the end is ordained, ſo the meanes muſt be uſed: God doth and will pardon ſinne, and therefore we muſt pray
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:173875:122" rendition="simple:additions"/>for pardon, as a meanes or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained. Thirdly, prayer doth not prejudice the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of a thing: Chriſt prayeth for that hee was moſt ſure of, <hi>Iohn</hi> 17. <hi>I pray for them which thou haſt given me, for they are thine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pregnant for the proofe of this point,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.3, 4, 5.</note> is that of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Wee are begotten againe to a lively hope,</hi> a <hi>hope</hi> of that life which maketh <hi>live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> Oh but wee are weake! true, but <hi>wee are kept by the power of GOD:</hi> an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance is not onely kept for us, but we are kept for it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> But Sathan is ſtrong, and his malice is more than his ſtrength?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> True, but wee are <hi>kept</hi> as by a Gariſon, wee
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:173875:123" rendition="simple:additions"/>have a guard about us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> All this is true, while faith holdeth out; but that may faile?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> No, we are kept by the power of GOD <hi>through faith;</hi> God keepeth our faith, and us by faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> But the time is long betweene us and ſalvation, and many dangers may fall out?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Be it ſo that the time is long, yet wee are kept <hi>unto ſalvation,</hi> even untill the <hi>day of Redemption:</hi> for the Spirit by vertue of the Covenant, puts the feare of GOD into our hearts, that wee ſhall never depart from him: GOD doth not promiſe what wee ſhall doe of ourſelves, but what he will doe in us, and
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:173875:123"/>by us. Thus the holy Ghoſt putteth a ſhield in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our hands to ward off all objections; and helpes us to ſubdue the reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings that are apt to riſe within us againſt this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed hope. So that this happy condition is not onely ſure to us, but God hath aſſured us of it.<note place="margin">Why God aſſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> us of our ſalvation.</note> Gods gracious indulgence is ſuch, hee ſees here wee goe through a wilderneſſe, and are moleſted every way, therefore he would have us aſſured of a bleſſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to come. So good is God, hee doth not onely finde out a glorious way of Redemption by the bloud of his Sonne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> God-Man, but hee acquaints us with
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:173875:124" rendition="simple:additions"/>it in the dayes of our pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage.<note place="margin">1 For his glory.</note> Partly, that wee may glorifie him, that hee may have the praiſe before hand of what good hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends us: for aſſurance of that bleſſed condition will ſtirre up our ſpirits to bleſſe God. What the thing it ſelfe would worke, Faith workes the ſame in ſome meaſure. Therefore Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. <hi>Bleſſed be God</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>who hath begotten us againe to a lively hope of an inheritance immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, underfiled, that fadeth not away, reſerved in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens.</hi> Why doth hee bleſſe God before we have it? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee are as ſure of it as if wee had it: what is revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led before hand, is praiſed for before hand. GOD
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:173875:124"/>would have us aſſured, that he may have glory.</p>
               <p>Partly to comfort us:<note place="margin">2 For our comfort.</note> for Faith is effectuall to worke that comfort that the thing preſent would doe in ſome meaſure. What comfort would the ſoule have, if it ſhould ſee heaven open, and it ſelfe entring into it, if re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption were at hand? The ſame Faith workes in ſome meaſure. What is more ſure then the thing it ſelf? What more comfortable then Faith in it?</p>
               <p>When the Iſraelites were in the wilderneſſe going to Canaan, they had many promiſes that they ſhould come to Canaan, and many extraordinary helpes to leade them thither; the pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and cloud, and Angell:
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:173875:125" rendition="simple:additions"/>and God out of indulgence condeſcending to their weakneſſe, gave them ſome grapes of Canaan: he put it into the minde of the ſpies to bring of the fruits. So God give us ſome work of his bleſſed Spirit, whereby hee would have us aſſured, and ſealed to the day of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</p>
               <p>The third concluſion is this,<note place="margin">The third concluſion</note> that <hi>the ſpirit doth ſeale us.</hi> This cannot bee other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, for who can eſtabliſh us in the love of God, but he that knowes the minde of God towards us; and who knowes the minde of God, but the ſpirit of God?</p>
               <p>Then am I ſealed, when I doe not onely beleeve, but by a reflecting act of the ſoule, know I doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve:
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:173875:125" rendition="simple:additions"/>and this reflection though it be by Reaſon, yet it is by Reaſon inabled by the Spirit; our ſpirits by the Spirit onely can diſcerne of ſpirituall acts: it is not for us to know things above na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, without a cauſe above nature. None can know the meaning of our broken deſires, ſo as to helpe us in our infirmities, but that Spirit that ſtirred up thoſe deſires. Againe, none knowes the grievances of our ſpirits, but our owne ſpirits, and the Spirit of God, who knowes all the turnings and corners of the ſoule.</p>
               <p>Who can mortifie thoſe ſtrong corruptions, that would hinder us in the way to heaven, but the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:173875:126" rendition="simple:additions"/>cloathing our ſpirit with power from above? who pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifieth the conſcience, but he that is above co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience? Who can raiſe our ſpirits a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove al temptations &amp; trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, but that Spirit of power that is above all?</p>
               <p>The ſtrength and vigour of any creature is from the ſpirits: and the ſtrength of the ſpirits of all fleſh is from this Spirit, whoſe office is to put ſpirit into our ſpirit.</p>
               <p>As GOD redeemed us with his bloud, ſo GOD muſt apply this bloud, that conſcience may bee quie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Hee onely can ſubdue the rebellion of our ſpirits, and ſoften our hearts, and make them fit for ſealing. The Spirit onely can ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the mercy of God to
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:173875:126"/>our ſouls, as to perſwade and worke our hearts to this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, otherwiſe wee would never yeeld. For part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the greatneſſe of the ſtate is ſuch, that none but God can aſſure: and partly the miſgiving and unbeliefe of our heart is ſuch, that none but God can ſubdue it. The thing being ſo great, and our deſervings ſo little, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unworthy of the things of this life, much more of that eternall happineſſe; this cannot be done without the high and glorious Spirit of God.</p>
               <p>How earneſt and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous then is both the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Sonne to ſave us, that pleaſed to ſend ſuch an Orator and Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor as is equall with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:173875:127" rendition="simple:additions"/>to perſwade us, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure us, to fit us for ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? and how gracious is the Spirit that will vouchſafe to have ſuch communion with ſuch poore fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>full ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits as ours? And ſhould not this worke upon our hearts a care not to grieve the holy Spirit? and ſo wee come to the fourth conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p>The fourth concluſion is,<note place="margin">The forth concluſion</note> that <hi>the ſealing of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit unto ſalvation, ſhould bee a ſtrong prevailing argument not to grieve the Spirit,</hi> that is, not to ſinne: for ſinne onely grieves the Spirit.<note place="margin">Tit, 2.11.12.</note> 
                  <hi>The grace of God</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Titus</hi>) <hi>that bringeth ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> Chriſt appeared: and what is Chriſt but grace? Chriſt appeared, and the
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:173875:127"/>free favour of GOD in Chriſt, whereby wee are aſſured of ſalvation: <hi>which teacheth us,</hi> what to doe? <hi>to deny all ungodlineſſe and worldly luſts, and to live ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly, righteouſly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and godly in this preſent world.</hi> Even the conſideration of the benefits of Chriſt, that are paſt, ſuch as came with Chriſts firſt comming, but that is not all, Verſe 13. <hi>Looking for that bleſſed hope, and the glorious appearing of the great God and our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> The ſecond comming of Chriſt enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth likewiſe the ſame care of holin fle.<note place="margin">Phil. 3.20</note> 
                  <hi>Our converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is in heaven,</hi> and not as theirs (ſpoken of in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Verſe) whoſe end is damnation, whoſe belly is
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:173875:128"/>their GOD, who minde earthly things: no, we minde heavenly things, and theſe heavenly deſires from whence ſprung they, but from the certaine <hi>expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Saviour the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, who ſhall change our vile bodies, &amp;c.</hi> that is, ſhall redeeme us fully even our bodies as well as our ſoules.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">It is an argument to them that are 1 Not ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</note>It is an argument of force, whether we be not yet ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, or be ſealed: if not ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, then gieve not him whoſe onely office it is to ſeale, entertaine his moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, give way to him, that hee may have ſcope andli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of working.</p>
               <p>Set no reaſons againſt his reaſons, hearken to no counſell againſt his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell,
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:173875:128"/>ſtand not out his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions any longer, but yeeld up your ſpirits to him, leſt hee put a perio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to his patience: hee is <hi>long</hi> ſuffering, but not <hi>alwayes</hi> ſuffering: if hee give us up to our own ſpirits, wee ſhall onely be witty to worke out our owne damnation: wee are not given up to our owne ſpirits, but after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny repulſes of this holy Spirit: and at length, what now will not ſerve for an argument to perſwade us, ſhall bee uſed hereafter as an argument to torment us. The Spirit will helpe our ſpirits to repeate and recall all the motions to our owne good, that wee formerly put backe. Wee ſhould thinke when con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:173875:129"/>ſpeakes in us, God ſpeakes, and when the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit moves us, it is God that moves us, and that all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe will be cut off: anſwere will bee, did not I tell you of this by conſcience, my deputy? did not I move you to this good by mine owne Spirit? Take heed of keeping out any light, for light, where it doth not come in and ſoften, har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens: none ſo hard hearted, as thoſe upon whom the light hath ſhined: there is more to bee hoped from a man, that hath onely a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall conſcience, then from him, whoſe heart and ſpirit hath beene long bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten on: there is more to bee hoped from a heathen <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late,</hi> than a proud Phariſee.
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:173875:129"/>Thoſe that will not bee ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to their ſalvation, it is juſt with GOD that they ſhould be ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>led up to their deſtruction; the ſoule with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſpirit is darkeneſſe and confuſion, full of ſelfe accuſing and ſelfe tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts: it we let the Spirit come in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it will ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all, and ſettle the ſoule in aſweet quiet.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2 Thoſe that are ſealed ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a 1 Leſſer degree.</note>For thoſe that have beene ſealed by the Spirit, and yet not ſo fully, as to ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence all doubts, about their eſtate: thoſe ſhould out of that beginning of comfort which they feele, ſtudy to bee pliable to the Spirit, for further increaſe. The Spirit ſealeth by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees: as our care of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Spirit increaſeth,
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:173875:130" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſo our comfort increaſeth; our light will increaſe as the morning light unto the perfect day. Yeelding to the Spirit in one holy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, will cauſe him to leade us to another, and ſo on forwards untill wee bee more deepely acquainted with the whole counſell of God concerning our ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: otherwiſe if wee give way to any contrary luſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> darkeneſſe will grow upon our Spirits unawares, and we ſhall be left in an unſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led condition, as thoſe that travaile in the twi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, that cannot perfectly finde out their way. Wee ſhall be on and off, not da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to yeeld wholly to our luſts, becauſe of a worke of grace begun: nor yeeld
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:173875:130"/>wholly to the Spirit, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we have let ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly affection get too much ſtrength in us, and ſo our ſpirits are without comfort, and our profeſſion without glory.</p>
               <p>We ſhall lye open to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, if hee be let looſe to winnow our Faith: for if our ſtate come to bee que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned, wee have nothing to alledge but the truth of our graces: and if wee have not uſed the Spirit well, we ſhall not have power to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge them, nor to looke upon any grace wrought in us, but upon thoſe luſts and ſinnes whereby wee have grieved the Spirit; they will bee ſet in order before us, and ſo ſtare us in the face, that wee cannot
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:173875:131"/>but fixe our thoughts upon them. And Sathan will not loſe ſuch an advantage, but will tempt us to call the worke of grace in queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: which though it bee a true worke, yet for want of light of the Spirit to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne it, wee cannot ſee it to our comfort. Whereas if the Spirit would witneſſe unto us the truth of our ſtate, and the ſincerity of our graces, wee ſhall bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to hold our owne, and thoſe temptations will va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2 Thoſe that are ſealed in a higher degree.</note>For thoſe that the holy Spirit hath ſet a clearer and ſtronger ſtampe upon, that doe not queſtion their condition, they of all others ſhould not grieve the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="237" facs="tcp:173875:131"/>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> A Spirit of ingenuity will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inder them, and ſtirre up <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhame in them to requite ſo ill, ſuch a friend. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo ingenuous as grace: what is commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in nature, is in greater perfection in grace. How doth the conſcience of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindeneſſe to a friend that hath deſerved well of us, trouble our ſpirits, that wee know not with what face to looke upon him? And will not unkindeneſſe to the Spirit make us aſhamed to lift up our face to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven?</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Benefits are bonds, and the greater favour, the ſtronger obligation; now what greater favour is there, then for the Spirit to renew us according to
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:173875:132"/>the Image of God our glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Saviour: who carried the Image of Sathan be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? And by this to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate us unto GOD, to be laid up in his treaſure, as carrying his ſtampe, and by this to bee ſeparated from the vile condition of the world; although wee carry in us the ſeeds of the ſame corruption that the worſt doth, differing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from them but in GODS free grace and the fruits of it. For God to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme ſo of us, that have no worthineſſe of our owne, but altogether per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons not worthy to bee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved: as to make our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe a foile, to ſet out the freeneſſe of his love; in making us worthy,
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:173875:132"/>whom he found not ſo. For the Spirit by ſealing of us to ſecure us in the midſt of all ſpirituall dangers: and to hide us as this ſecret ones, that <hi>that evill one</hi> ſhould not touch us to hurt us. Theſe, as they are fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of an high nature, the more care they require to walke worthy of them. We cannot but forget our ſelves, before wee yeeld to any thing againſt that dignity the Spirit hath ſealed us to.</p>
               <p>Nature helped with or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary education, moveth every man to carry him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe anſwerable to his condition: a Magiſtrate as a Magiſtrate, a Subject as a Subject, a Childe as a Childe; and wee thinke it
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:173875:133"/>diſgracefull to doe other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: and ſhall that which is diſgracefull to nature, not be much more diſgrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to nature renewed, and advanced by the Spirit? And indeed as wee ſhould not, ſo wee cannot grieve the Spirit ſo farre forth as wee are renewed.<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.</note> Our new nature will not ſuffer us to diſſemble, to be worldly, to bee carnall, as the world is, wee cannot but ſtudy holineſſe, wee cannot but be for GOD and his truth, wee cannot but expreſſe what we are, and whoſe wee are.</p>
               <p>It is impoſſible a man ſhould care for heaven, that doth not care for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings of heaven: hee cannot bee ſaid to care for
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:173875:133"/>full redemption and glory, that doth not care for the ſpirit of grace: fulneſſe of grace is the beſt thing in glory; other things, as peace and joy, and the like, they are but the ſhinings forth of this fulneſſe of grace in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
               <p>Againe, when the Spirit aſſureth us of Gods love in the greateſt fruits of it, as it doth when it aſſureth this redemption: That love kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles love againe, and love conſtraines us, by a ſweet neceſſity to yeeld cheerefull and willing obedience in all things: there is nothing more active and fuller of inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, than love, and there is nothing that love ſtudies more than how to pleaſe, there is nothing that it fears
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:173875:134"/>more than to diſcontent. It is a neate affection, and will indure nothing offenſive, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to it ſelfe, or the ſpirit of ſuch as we love: and this love the Spirit teaches the heart, &amp; love teaches us not onely our duty, but to doe it in a loving and acceptable manner. It carries out the whole ſtreame of the ſoule with it, and rules all, whileſt it rules, &amp; will not ſuffer the ſoule to divert to by-things, much leſſe to contrary.</p>
               <p>Againe, theſe graces that are converſant about that condition which the Spirit aſſureth us of, as faith and hope, are purging and puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying graces, working a ſuteableneſſe in the ſoule, to the things beleeved, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for: and the excellency
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:173875:134" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the things beleeved &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for, have ſuch a work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the ſoule, that it wil not ſuffer the ſoul to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file it ſelfe. Our hopes on high, will leade us to wayes on high, therefore whileſt theſe graces are exerciſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout theſe objects, the ſoule cannot but bee in a pleaſing frame.</p>
               <p>It hath been an old cavill, that certainty of ſalvation breeds ſecurity &amp; looſeneſſe of life. And what is there that an ill diſpoſed ſoul can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſucke poyſon out of? A man may as truely ſay, the Sea burns, or the Fire cools: there is nothing quickens a ſoule more to cheerefull o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, than aſſurance of Gods love, &amp; that our <hi>labour</hi> ſhould <hi>not bee in vaine in the
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:173875:135" rendition="simple:additions"/>Lord;</hi> this is the Scriptures Logick and Rhetorick to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force and perſwade a holy life from knowledge of our preſent eſtate in grace. <hi>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you by the mercies of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 12.</note> ſaith Saint <hi>Paul:</hi> what mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies? ſuch as he had ſpoken of before. Iuſtification, San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, Aſſurance that all ſhall worke together for good, that nothing ſhall bee able to ſeparate us from the love of God in Chriſt: all duties tend to aſſurance, or ſpring from aſſurance.</p>
               <p>Gods intendment is to bring us to heaven by a way of love, and cheerefulneſſe; as all his wayes towards us in our ſalvation, are in love. And this is the ſcope of the covenant of grace; and for this end hee ſends the Spirit
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:173875:135" rendition="simple:additions"/>of adoption into our hearts, that we may have a childe-like liberty with God in all our addreſſes to him. When he offers himſelfe to us as a father, it is fit we ſhould of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer our ſelves to him as chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; nature teaches a child, the more hee deſires his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers love, the more he fears to diſpleaſe him. And hee is judged to be graceleſſe, that will therefore venture to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his father, becauſe hee knowes hee neither can, or will diſinherit him. Certaine it is, the more ſurely wee know God hath begotten us to ſo glorious aninheritance, the more it will worke upon our bowels, to take all to heart that may any way touch him: this wrought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>David,</hi> when the Prophet
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:173875:136"/>told him, God hath done this and this for thee, and <hi>would have done more, if that had beene too little,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.</note> it melted him preſently into an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble confeſſion. Thoſe that have felt the power of the Spirit of adoption on their hearts, will both by a divine inſtinct, as alſo by ſtrength of reaſon, bee carried to all thoſe courſes wherein they ſhall approve themſelves to their father. Inſtinct of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſtrengthened with grounds, wil move ſtrongly.</p>
               <p>To conclude this diſcourſe, let Chriſtians therefore bee carefull to preſerve and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh the worke of aſſurance and ſealing in them.</p>
               <p n="2">2 What God doth for us,<note place="margin">1. Meanes.</note> he doth by grace in us, he wil preſerve us that we ſhall not
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:173875:136"/>fall from him by putting the grace of feare into us, <hi>Ier.</hi> He will keep us, but by what means?<note place="margin">Phil. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>The peace of God which paſſeth all underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, ſhall guard our hearts.</hi> God maketh our Calling and Election ſure in us,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.</note> by ſtirring our hearts up to be diligently exerciſed in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding one grace unto ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and in growing in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry grace, as 2 <hi>Pet</hi> 1. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee muſt attend upon al ſpiritual means of growth and quickening: ſo ſhall you have a further <hi>entrance into the kingdome of Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> that is, you ſhall have more evident knowledge of your ent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce into the kingdom of grace here, and likewiſe into the kingdome of glory here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. Thoſe that do not ſo,
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:173875:137" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhall have no comfort either from the time paſt, for they ſhall <hi>forget they were purged from their ſinnes,</hi> or from thoughts of the time to come, for they ſhall not bee able to ſee things <hi>farre off.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 If aſſurance be in a leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer degree,<note place="margin">2 Meanes.</note> yet yeeld not to temptations and carnall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings: if our evidences be not ſo faire, yet we will not part with our inheritance. Coynes, as old groates, that have little of the ſtamp left, yet are currant. We loſe our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort many times, becauſe wee yeeld ſo eaſily, becauſe wee have not ſuch a ſtrong and cleare ſeale of ſalvation as wee would, to bee borne downe that we have none at all, is a great weakeneſſe: ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe therefore the little
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:173875:137" rendition="simple:additions"/>faith thou haſt in ſtriving a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch objections, and it will bee a meanes to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the ſeale of the Spirit.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Becauſe this ſealing is gradually,<note place="margin">3 Meanes.</note> wee ſhould pray as <hi>Paul, Epheſ.</hi> 1. <hi>for a ſpirit of revelation,</hi> that wee may be more ſealed: (the Ephefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans were ſealed, for whom <hi>Paul</hi> prayes, and ſo the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſians; yet) that GOD would reveale to their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, more their excellent co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.<note place="margin">Col. 2.2.</note> There are <hi>riches of aſſurance,</hi> the Apoſtle would have the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> labour not only for aſſurance, but for the riches of it, that will bring rich comfort, and joy and peace. Times of temptations and tryall may come, and ſuch as, if we have not ſtrong aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, wee may be ſorely
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:173875:138" rendition="simple:additions"/>troubled, and call all into queſtion. This may be the ſad condition of Gods owne children, and from this, that in times of peace, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented themſelves with a leſſer degree of this aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and ſealing.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Laſtly,<note place="margin">4 Meanes.</note> be watchfull o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver your owne hearts and wayes, that according to what you have now learned, you grieve not the ſpirit, <hi>for by it you are ſealed,</hi> intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that if in any thing wee withſtand and grieve the ſpirit, wee ſhall in ſo doing, prejudice our ſelves, and ſuffer in the comfort and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of our ſealing.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:173875:138"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173875:139"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
